<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A continuation of the lamentable and admirable adventures of Dom Sebastian king of Portugale With a declaration of all his time employed since the battell in Africke against the infidels 1578. vntill this present yeare 1603.</title>
            <author>Teixeira, José, 1543-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23866</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837085</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1393</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1393)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 978:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A continuation of the lamentable and admirable adventures of Dom Sebastian king of Portugale With a declaration of all his time employed since the battell in Africke against the infidels 1578. vntill this present yeare 1603.</title>
                  <author>Teixeira, José, 1543-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Field] for Iames Shaw, and are to be sold at his shop neare Ludgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By José Teixeira.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 210) on title page.</note>
                  <note>A suppositious history concerning one of the pretenders to the throne of Portugal after the death of Sebastião in 1578.--Folger Library Catalogue.</note>
                  <note>A translation of the French original.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sebastiao, --  King of Portugal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1393:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1393:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONTINVATION OF THE LAMENTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BLE AND ADMIRABLE AD<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VENTVRES OF DOM SEBA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STIAN KING OF POR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TVGALE.</p>
            <p>With a declaration of all his time employed ſince the battell in Africke againſt the Infidels 1578. vntill this preſent yeare 1603.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>ANCHORA SPEI</head>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>Iames Shaw,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neare Ludgate. 1603.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1393:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:1393:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, in the entrance of this Diſcourſe which followes, you ſhall find three letters written by an auncient man called Doctor <hi>Texere</hi> a Portugal, directed to a Biſhop this fathers verie friend, which I haue here compiled and expreſſed among other proofes to veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the infortunate accidents this diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous King hath ſustained, ſince he was taken priſoner by the great Duke of Tuſcane, vntill the laſt day of the yeare paſt <hi>1601.</hi> You may alſo find within this Pamphlet two Letters tranſlated: one written by <hi>D. Raimond Marqueti,</hi> a Knight of the order of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> borne in Meſsina in Sicile to <hi>Dom Sebaſtian;</hi> the other ſent from the ſaid King to <hi>D. Proſpero Baracco,</hi> dwelling in Padua. By the two last letters it will euidently appeare vnto you, that the priſoner detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned now in Naples, is not that <hi>Marco Tullio Catizone,</hi> whom the Spaniards in their libels haue ſo falſly proclaimed; but the very true King of Portugale <hi>Dom Sebaſtian.</hi> Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after theſe letters followeth a diſcourſe, in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning whereof there is a Preface written by father <hi>Texere,</hi> manifeſting the naturall diſpoſition of Portugals, and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing how conſtantly they addreſſe themſelues in loyaltie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their Gouernours that raigne ouer them, according to the ſincere word of God, and the vnfallible rules of honour.</p>
            <p>You may alſo behold a moſt ample declaration, about the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1393:3"/>end of this diſcourſe, miniſtring foure ſeuerall points, worthie the reading and obſeruing; to proue vnto you aſſuredly, that the priſoner for whom we trauell ſo induſtriouſly with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuerance, is the true and lawfull King of Portugale <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> whom God of his diuine mercie will (I truſt) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to his former Crowne and dignitie, for the good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagation of the peace and welfare of all Chriſtendome: which the eternall God effect, if it be his bleſſed will. Amen. The <hi>26.</hi> of Feb. An. <hi>1602.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1393:3"/>
            <head>A Letter ſent from father Fr. IO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEPH TEXERE <hi>to a Biſhop.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ost accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> benedictionem.</hi> I wrote to your reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Lordſhip fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paris, to ſignifie vnto you the cauſe of my returne from Lions, where I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your L. dated the 20. of March. In the which you gaue me in charge that if I had occaſion to trauell into Laly, I ſhould giue you ſpeciall intelligence of all the occurrents that ſhould be preſented to my vnderſtanding in my iourney: the 16. of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill in the ſame yeare I departed from Paris, towards theſe parts, paſſing through Campaigne: the very firſt day the gout began to aſſaile me, and ceaſſed not, but accompanied me to Chalons, which was wedneſday being holyday; where I remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my couent vntill the wedneſday after Eaſter.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, after dinner (hauing vrgent occaſion) I was compelled by meanes of my ſickneſſe to vſe the benefite of a coach, and came the Friday following to Nance. On Saterday following I vndertooke to walke faire and ſoftly with much paine, to viſit his Highneſſe, and the Ladie ſiſter to the King, and her husband, the Cardinall, the Count of Vandemont, and the Princeſſe his ſiſter. Beleeue me I cannot expreſſe in words the conſolation I conceiued, in beholding the inſeparable bond of loue and amitie, wherein theſe noble Princes ſeemed to be vnited and conformed: from whom like one loaden and charged with honourable benefits, giftes, graces, and fauours, I depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Baſil on munday being the ſeuenth of May. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great confort my entertainement gaue me occaſion of, yet bitter ſpell of diſcontentment wounded me inwardly; for that the friday before, I had particular intelligence by the poſt, that the Calabrian, the falſe and counterfeit <hi>Dom Sebastian,</hi> as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1393:4"/>they termed him, the pretended King of Portugale, was ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred into the cuſtodie of the gouernor of Orbetelo, a towne in Tuſcane bordering vpon the Mediterranian ſea, being a part of the King of Spaines territories, from thence to be conueyed to the Viceroy of Naples: ſo ſwift were thoſe bloudie Spaniards in their cruel expeditions. The poore Prince departed from that towne the 13 of Aprill, at eleuen of the clocke at night, paſſing by Siene the foure and twentieth, and was deliuered the ſixe and twentieth. The manner of diuulging theſe newes, was by intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence that came to Nance by Milan in leſſe then eight dayes. The eleuenth of May I came to Baſill: the thirteenth I entred Soleurre, where becauſe I was ill at eaſe, <hi>Monſieur de Vic</hi> (your Lordſhips deare friend) and worthie Ambaſſadour of his moſt Chriſtian Maieſtie in affaires to the Swiſſers and Griſons, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced me to ſtay and repoſe my ſelfe with him, vntill the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day: wherehence after the fruition of infinite courteſies I departed, paſſing by the Swiſſers, Griſons, Valtoline, and Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camonica, I entred into Italy: the firſt towne I lodged in was Breſſe, the next Verona, Vicence, Padua. The ſecond of Iune I came to Venice, where without delay I haſted to viſit <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illiers</hi> Ambaſſador of his excellent Maieſtie. This noble gentleman I found in all reſpects as your Lordſhip had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended him to me, moſt reuerend for honour, vertue, and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as the world can iuſtly teſtifie. From thence I retired my ſelfe in his Gundelo to a friend of mine, an honourable gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, by whom with diuers other of my friends that came to ſee me, I was confirmed in my former knowledge, concerning the miſhaps before rehearſed; vnderſtanding in like maner, how grieuouſly the nobles and citizens of Venice, tooke the troubles of the worthie diſtreſſed King, aſcribing the blame to the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence of the Portugals, that vndertooke the managing of his libertie, into whoſe hands they had committed him ſafe and ſound: for as much as in thoſe Lords preſence, they ſeemed to acknowledge him, vnder which pretence they preaſed before the Senate, to ſignifie vnto them a truth, beſeeching them to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him ſome other ſolemnitie in proceeding, then they vſe to a common or priuate perſon, and to reſpect him as a King. The
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1393:4"/>fourth day I returned to Padua: the ſeuenth I was at breake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in Mantua, where I was well entertained by the reuerend and vertuous Prelate, the rare and honourable Lord Fr. <hi>Francis Gonzaga,</hi> Biſhop of the ſaid citie. And ſoone after I had bene in my couent, and receiued the chiefe Prelates benediction, I went to ſalute the Duke and the Ducheſſe, to whom I caried certaine letters, who receiued me with no leſſe ſhew of account then they could haue made to an Ambaſſadour that had bene employed in the moſt Chriſtian Kings affaires.</p>
            <p>The ſelfe ſame day to accompanie this my glorious enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement, the deſpitefull gout made a returne into my feeble limmes, and there ſoiourned with me ſeuenteene or eighteene dayes in the ſame citie. In which ſpace I drew a tree with bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, expreſſing the genealogie of the houſe of Gonzaga; wherewith the Duke ſeemed ſo well pleaſed, that he gaue me a great preſent in gratification. I proteſt I ſhould neuer haue dreamed that Mantua had bene honoured with a Prince ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble for vertue, ſo rare for honourable courteſie, ſo peereleſſe for bountie, ſo familiar in hiſtories, ſo conuerſant in languages, ſo great a louer of rare properties, ſo intire a Chriſtian. I ſifted diuers of his Court as narrowly as I might poſſibly, and I diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered them to be true and faithfull wel-willers to our countrey of France.</p>
            <p>On the feaſt day of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> ſomewhat late I ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in my iourney towards Ferrara through Bologne: on the eight and twentith day of the laſt moneth I came to Ferrara, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>S. Peters</hi> eue: the next day being the feaſt day, after my morning repaſt, I went to the honourable Duke, deliuering him certaine letters, which he receiued with a ſmiling counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and made very faire weather to me by his honourable and courteous entertainement, ſo did likewiſe his Ducheſſe. All this while making no mention to me of the King, nor of the Calabrian, nor I to any man, the Duke and Ducheſſe ſeuerally demaunded of me what newes I heard of France or Lorayne, and ſo ſleighted me off with licence to depart, ſaying, we will take another day fitter to handle theſe cauſes more at large: ſo I departed for that time. The next day following, the Duke
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1393:5"/>came into our couent of <hi>S. Marke,</hi> where I remained, and our Prior intreated me to beare the Prouinciall companie to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Highneſſe at the Church porch: where the Duke took notice of me, and talked with me all the way paſſing through the entrie; and at his departure ſaid, I will chooſe a more conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient time to talke with you more at large. After breakefaſt I went to the Archbiſhop of Piſa, and deliuered him a letter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a very friend of his, in regard wherof he did me many kind offices. And I telling him, I had vndertaken this iourney for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch of buſineſſe that concerned my order and my ſelf particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarly, (for ſo was the tenor of my paſport) and to acquaint my lelfe in the families of the Princes of Italy: after long delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and pauſing for the ſpace of an houre, he demaunded of me if I had not heard any ſpeech of a Calabrian, that named him ſelfe <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portugale: to whom I anſwered, that being in the court of Lorayne, I vnderſtood by letters ſent from Milane that there was ſuch a counterfeit, and abuſer, and that therefore I would not meddle neither with him nor his affaires. And he replied vnto me, that he thought it not amiſſe for me to know what paſſed, and was done in that buſineſſe. When I found his purpoſe, I prepared my ſelfe to heare him as patiently as I could, and he very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly began this inuectiue which followeth.</p>
            <p>This man that would be called <hi>Dom Sebastian.</hi> &amp;<hi>c.</hi> is Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labrian, a merchant, whoſe name is <hi>Marco Tullio Cati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zone,</hi> that hath both wife and children aliue, which haue bene compelled to come from Meſſina to go to Naples to iuſtifie the truth. And the ſame Calabrian hath had acceſſe to Portugal for matters of trafficke, where ſome religious profeſſors of our or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der haue perſwaded him to call and proclaime himſelfe <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portugale: and the Monke hath burned and branded him with hote yrons, in the ſame places with the like markes that <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> had: and the ſcarre which he carieth in his arme, was forced by a gaſh giuen of purpoſe with his owne hand, and the Monke that on his head. Beſide, when he was firſt taken he had only two crownes about him: and aſſoone as the Venetians diſcharged him, the Portugals conſulted how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1393:5"/>they might imbarke him at Liuorne, and ſend him preſently into France. Wherof the great Duke being ſpeedily aduertiſed, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the paſſages to be laid betwixt Florence &amp; the ſea coaſt, that he could eſcape no way: and ſo ſoone as he ſaw himſelf pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented and caught, he ſtraightway diſcouered his legerdemain, ſaying, that he was no longer able to endure thoſe torments and grieuous impriſonments, to maintaine ſuch fooliſh deluſions and coſinage. Preſuppoſed that before he made this confeſſion, he indented to haue his life aſſured him, which they aſcertained him of, comforting him that he ſhould not die. And after that he was detected in Naples by the preſence of his wife <hi>Donna Paula Catizzone,</hi> he was inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſent into Spaine, without any violence done vnto him, and was there openly and generally ſhewed to all the word, to the end that the Portugals ſhould no longer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe him, and that it might be publiſhed to the world, that he was a very impoſtor, a counterfeit, and a deluder. After I heard ſo many fooliſh and groſſe abſurdities vttered ſo confidently, my very ſoule was ſo deeply plunged into extreme griefe and vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I was forced to craue pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d lord, for not anſwering, being ſore perplexed: knowing aſſuredly, that that <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> died in Portugale, while he indeuored the diſpatch of ſome buſineſſe the King ſent him thither about: which is euident by a letter ſent from one <hi>D. Raimond Marqueti</hi> a Knight dwelling in Meſſina, by whoſe meanes and perſwaſion the King ſent this <hi>Marco</hi> into Portugale. Which letter was ſent by <hi>Marqueti</hi> to Venice to haue bin deliuered to <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> which came to the Venetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hands, whereof the lords of Venice cauſed a copie to be taken, and the originall remaines in the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtodie of one <hi>Conſtantine Nicoline,</hi> citizen and inhabitant of the ſame citie, wherehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a tranſcript was made, which I haue about me to ſhew. This <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſeeing the agents of Spaine to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie an vntruth ſo impudently without bluſhing, ſaying, that the priſoner was called <hi>Marco Catizzone;</hi> ſhewed this letter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly in <hi>S. Markes</hi> church, to ſtop and confound their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. Which letter when they had ſcene and peruſed, they were neuer afterward ſo bold as to proſecute the matter any further, but kept ſilence. Moreouer it appeared that this priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1393:6"/>could not be <hi>Marco Tullio</hi> by another letter, written by the priſoner to <hi>D. Proſpero Baracco,</hi> which he ſhewed me in Padua, which I craued earneſtly to haue deliuered me to bring with me, but I could onely obtaine a copie thereof, which I haue alſo in my cuſtody. The ſame is likewiſe teſtified by another letter from an Italian gentleman, attending the moſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> king. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is deſirous to ſee the ſaid letter, ſhal find it in the beginning of the booke, called, <hi>Admirable aduentures, &amp;c.</hi> which was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed in France before I came from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towards theſe parts. I haue ſet downe theſe proceedings in writing to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, to acquaint you with the forgerie and deuiſes of thoſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractors, called Caſtilians. Now to returne to the Archbiſhop of Piſa, whom I cannot but charge with great abuſe, to report that thoſe naturall markes were inſeared with a hot iron, and to lay it vpon a religious Monke of mine owne order. But to ſet aſide many reaſons and proofes that might eaſily confute his allegations, this one ſhall ſerue to ſatisfie all men that haue any ſparke of diſcretion or iudgement; It is impoſſible that any man ſhould by art, force, or skil, make a mans right arme and leg big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in all proportions, then the left: that is only reſerued to God that made him.</p>
            <p>And further, this reuerend Lord would haue perſwaded me, that the religious man that ſo marked him was <hi>D. Sampayo:</hi> which was impoſſible to be true, for the ſaid father neuer once ſaw the King ſince he departed from Lisbone to go into Afrike, vntill the eleuenth of December laſt paſt, when he was ſet at libertie by the Venetians. Beſide, this <hi>D. Sampayo</hi> neuer knew any priuie marks of the Kings bodie vntil the yeare of our Lord 1599. that he went into Portugale to inquire of them. Hearing ſo many reports ſo much differing, and knowing how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Archbiſhop could hide his owne errour: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that to anſwer him peremptorily, might rather hurt then further my purpoſe: and to ſaue my ſelfe from perill, being within his iuriſdiction, I was faine to ſuppreſſe my inward paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but ſaid vnto him: My Lord, ſeeing you vnderſtand that the impriſonment of this man was the chiefe cauſe of my arriual in theſe parts, and as I vnderſtand the honourable Knight came
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1393:6"/>from thence, being foure times ſent for by letters fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paris to the great Duke, ſithence I was in Loraine, whatſoeuer is or ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of his perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or affaires I reſolue herafter to take litle care, but meane to follow the other employment I recounted to your lordſhip. Notwithſtanding, as one that hath ſome intereſt in the cauſe, I will render your Lordſhip my cenſure and reſolution in a word, and make you partaker of my inward and ſecret con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templations. Foraſmuch as your lordſhip hath acquainted with this impoſtor and deluders confeſſion, diſſimulation, and trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peries, I can do no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grieue thereat very much, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he eſcaped without puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, being (as your lordſhip aſſures me he is) ſo vile and ſo notorious an offender, maruelling you would ſuffer ſo peſtilent and damnable a wretch to liue, that hath bene the cauſe of ſo many mens diſaſters, confiſcation of goods, ruines, and extinguiſhments, by vndertaking miſaduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures by ſea &amp; land, and what not indemnities for his ſake, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning countrie, father, mother, wife, children, houſe and home, reſt and ſafetie: and I wonder it pleaſed God to ſuffer ſuch a one to be borne, that his mother in his conception, before her deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance, had not bene transformed into a ſtone, or preſently bin diſſolued into ſmoke or aire.</p>
            <p>What vnhappie man could haue cauſed me to forſake my place in Paris, where I was well and quietly ſeated, to thruſt my life into perill, but onely he? that wicked and vngodly man. I haue twiſe in this vnluckie iorney bene afflicted with the gout: diuers times almoſt ouerwhelmed with ſnow, drenched in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, tormented with clambring rocks and hils, ſuſtaining all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards that ſea and land might preſent me, with thunder and lightning from clouds: and is it iuſtice thinke you (my good Lord) that a man occaſioning ſo many troubles, ſhould liue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? This man hath troubled me much, and grieued my very ſoule. This (noble Duke) might by the aproueme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of many, haue cauſed him to haue bene indited, arraigned, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and haue miniſtred to him ſome extraordinarie death, to the terrible example of all others, and haue manifeſted the ſame to all the world. In my conceit, my noble Lord, this execution had bin moſt expedient &amp; conuenient, to the commendation of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1393:7"/>equitie and iuſtice. The Archbiſhop hearing theſe words pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced with ſuch vehement paſſion, as though my ſoule had giuen franke conſent to my paſſionate vtterance, in lamentation of my hard ſucceſſe, ſaid: I am much grieued for your vexation: notwithſtanding I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſo hainouſly accuſe nor condemne the man, but only for his folly to call himſelfe <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> king of Portugal: for ſurely he was a reuerend man for vertue and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of life. I could rather agree to accuſe that Religious trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, by whom he was firſt perſwaded and ſuborned to take the name of King vpon him. Theſe &amp; many ſuch like words he vſed aſwell to iuſtifie himſelfe, as to recouer me out of that affliction, which he perceiued his ſpeeches had thruſt me into; but in the end I took my leaue of his lordſhip, and returned to my cloiſter of <hi>S. Mark,</hi> where the religious fathers receiued with many cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies and kind welcomes. The like entertainment I found in all other couents as I went, ſpecially at Mantua, where I was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned to remaine many daies. God giue me abilitie &amp; grace to requite them, that I may not be found vnthankfull; for I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your Lordſhip, I cannot expreſſe the merites and fauours I found at their hands, much leſſe ſee which way I may yeeld them due recompence. From Mantua I thought beſt to go to Rome: in hope by the friendſhip of the Cardinals, and other noble Lords and Gentlemen, to find ſome furtherance in my affaires, to the bettering of my vnhappie Princes fortunes. That he ſhould be my very king and lord, I am greatly fortified in hope, &amp; find many good ſignes and apparant arguments amongſt the moſt ſerious and religious men of eſtimation, Princes, Lords, and others: finding it not expedient to nominate all the fauorers of this enterpriſe, deſiring your Lordſhip to pardon me for not ſatisfying you in euery particular, concerning my ſucceſſe at this time according to your requeſt: which defects I will repaire in my intelligence from Rome, from whence I hope to ſend your lordſhip more exact aduertiſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, concerning the life and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of this Prince ſince the battell in Africke, from whence he hardly eſcaped by flight: with al that paſt here in the time of his impriſonme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: how, in what maner, what day &amp; houre he depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted herehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Fa. <hi>Seraphin Banchi</hi> hath hitherto much aſſiſted me
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1393:7"/>in the buſineſſe, &amp; was very ioyfull of the honourable greetings from your Lordſhip, deſiring his continuance in your honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fauours. By his meanes I am ſo much furthered, as I truſt to morrow morning to be diſpatched hence. The Almightie bleſſe your honourable perſon in all you deſire. Florence the third of Iuly. 1601.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your noble Lordſhips humble ſeruant,</hi> father Fr. IOSEPH TEXERE Portugueze, &amp;c.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>A Letter written by the ſaid Fr. <hi>Texere</hi> to the Biſhop before ſaluted.</head>
            <p>IN my laſt Letter written to your excellent Lordſhip from Florence, I promiſed to performe as much, or rather more at my arriuall at Rome; wherein I feare I ſhall faile (for many cauſes checking my will and endeuour) to keepe touch with your Lordſhip. Firſt, becauſe I came not hither ſo ſoone as I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, being hindred by reaſon of my ſickneſſe which length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned my iorney: for being in Viterbe, I ſoiourned ſeuen or eight dayes in the houſe of our Ladie <hi>De la Quercia,</hi> a Monaſterie of our order, diſtant ſome halfe league from the towne, where God by the interceſſion of the Virgin doth many miracles, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the wel-beleeuers. So ſoone as I was entred into Rome, which was Sunday the fourteenth of Iuly, I ſought out my very friend, of whom I gathered, that his Holineſſe and all the Lords of the Court of Rome conceiued, and were perſwaded verily, that the priſoner which the Duke of Florence cauſed to be ſent therehence the three and twentith of Aprill at eleuen of the clock at night, and deliuered into the hands of the gouernour of <hi>Orbetelo,</hi> was <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> the true vnfallible King of Portugall. Of him I learned, how he was conducted from <hi>Orbetelo</hi> to <hi>Hercules</hi> port, and from that port in a galley to Naples, and laſt to Caſtelnouo. This gally the enemies made the ſubiect, to giue notice to the whole world, that the ſaid <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> was
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1393:8"/>condemned to the gallies, and after to the caſtle Del ouo. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I was ſhewed the copie of a letter, which the Count of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos Viceroy of Naples wrote to the Duke of Seſſa, Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour from the King of Caſtile vnto his Holineſſe, giuing him to vnderſtand, that the ſame priſoner was <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> the true King of Portugal. I haue alſo found out which of the Cardinals and Prelates fauour the cauſe of that vertuous and holy Prince. A friend of mine lent me his coach, wherein I went directly to the moſt excellent Prince, the Cardinall of Florence, and kiſt his hand, of whom I had the euidences your Lordſhip is aduiſed of, and after an houre and halfes conference with him, I departed in the ſame coach ſo viſit ſir <hi>Alexander Giuſti</hi> Iuſtice <hi>de la Rota,</hi> our deare friend. From whom ſo ſoone as I was departed, I met neare his gate with another of my familiar acquaintance, that diſcouered vnto me certaine plots and circumuentions at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted and ſuggeſted by the Duke of Seſſe, informing againſt me in the Conſiſtorie of Rome, that I was a ſeditious man, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall to the ſtate of Chriſtendome generally: for that hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Chriſtian Princes had vſed to aſſociate themſelues in a league ioyntly to make warre againſt the Infidels; which I had bene a cauſe to hinder, by interpoſing diuiſion and contention betwixt thoſe Princes; and as a principall reaſon to induce them to beleeue the ſame: he ſhewed publickly the diſcourſe which I ſent your Lordſhip from Lions, intituled, <hi>Admirable aduentures, &amp;c.</hi> which for the more familiar vnderſtanding was tranſlated into Italian and Spaniſh. The common diſperſing of which diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, was like to breede much diſhonour and damage to <hi>D. Philippo</hi> the third King of Caſtile his maiſter, and ſo purchaſe vnto himſelfe being his agent, infinite diſgrace and harme by his diſpleaſure. For my part I anſwered that I merited no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for traducing into writing ſuch true accidents (as they were) the confirmation whereof increaſed with the time: conſidering they were not of mine owne inuention or ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping. Relinquiſhing this friend, I haſted ſtraight to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Oſſat, into whoſe owne hands when I had deliuered letters, and informed him thoroughly of the cauſe of my repaire thither: he aduiſed me not to ſhew my ſelfe ſo openly there
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1393:8"/>vntill ſuch time as I vnderſtood what my enemies had conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to obiect againſt me ſince my entrance into this city, which could not be concealed, for that the Patriarke of Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (who was and is Generall of the Order of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> a Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian borne, and ſo much the more my forcible enemie, by how much he was zealous for the King of Caſtile his maiſter) had a glance of me in the Cardinall of Florence his houſe. My occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons detained me ſo long with this Cardinall till night grew on, ſo that his Lordſhip cauſed me to remaine with him vntill the morrow, wherehence after the hearing of his Maſſe, I departed to my firſt friends houſe: whither diuers perſons of qualitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired to viſit me, ſignifying vnto me, that the Ambaſſadour for Caſtile intended to work me all the miſchiefe he could poſſible: and ſeeing he found no ſufficient meanes to indamage me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eſtate, he had a purpoſe to bring me within compaſſe of the Inquiſition, alleaging theſe accuſations that follow. Firſt he obiected againſt me, that I had bene in England ſixe or ſeuen yeares, and that I euer fauoured the proceedings of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes; that I compoſed diuers bookes fraught with hereſies; that at Lions I made and began to imprint a booke againſt his Holineſſe, and the Inquiſitors generall of Portugale; with many other matters which I let paſſe for troubling your Lordſhip. To all which I anſwered without blemiſh to my honour or reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in this manner: I thanke God, all the time I was in England I liued amongſt men that were religious, as mine enemies can teſtifie: and for my continance in France, I hope to acquite my ſelfe eaſily from miſdemeanure there. To the moſt capitall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and of greateſt importance: that I wrote and began to print a booke at Lions againſt his Holineſſe, and the Inquiſitors generall of Portugale, I can purge my ſelfe purely, and paſſe as cleare as the moſt vnſpotted innocent, being alwayes appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued religious and zealous, wherein I appeale to the ſincerie of al the brethren of mine own order. In that he termes me a rebel and a traitor to the King his maiſter, for ſhewing my ſelf ſeruice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and faithfull to a forein Prince his enemie: in that he is aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to my affaires, recommending my eſtimation by opening a gap, to diſcipher the traiterous in Portugale, backſliders, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1393:9"/>to their owne friends, and very Caſtilian hypocrites: that I am a diſperſer of many lies, in conuenticles at this inſtant. That article is worthy of ſuch mens preferring as they ſeem to be, and not fitting men of worth and louers of Religion. As it hapneth I haue the booke about me, that was printed at Lions: which ſhall confute and diſplay the malice and impudencie of him that cauſed the reſt of my bookes to be burnt. The remainder that concernes theſe affaires, is beſt knowne to your Lordſhip, and therefore to conclude this point, I craue pardon for being ſo tedious. Now to returne to my former ſubiect. Sunday being the 15. of Iuly, and the Monday following, after I had finiſhed the principall part of my intention, I determined (by the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of my friends) to returne directly to France. And being aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed that the Duke of Seſſa had ſent beforehand ſome of his people to way-ly me in the ordinarie way, I changed my courſe by Vmbrie. I departed out of Rome the fourth day after my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall, and paſſing by the cities of Narne, Tarne, Spoleto, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligni, and Aſſiſe, I came to Peruſe, which I did onely paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, and ſhaped my courſe by Siene, Florence, Bologne, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the confines of Modene and Mirandole: and before I could reach to Mantua, my horſe fell vpon me, and hurt one of my legs very grieuouſly, which cauſed me to ſtay in this place, where I might prouide the beſt meanes for my recouerie. I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure your Lordſhip, I tooke this miſchance to be ominous, that God would haue it ſo, for that by my returne this by-way, I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered ſome certaintie of much that happened to <hi>Dom Sobaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the King, ſince his ſlight out of Africke, vntill he was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged out of this common-weale: and now I begin to make your Lordſhip a true relation, certaine, and without controle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. When it was ſpread at Rome that I remained in this town, and that by reaſon of my hurt I could not ſodainly depart from hence; a friend of mine certified me by letteers the ſixth of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, in what maner <hi>Paula Catizzone</hi> with her daughter arriued at Naples, being ſhipped from Meſſina by the Catholike Kings agents, to come and acknowledge this priſoner for her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: and the ſaid <hi>Paula</hi> meeting in the ſhip with a religious man of the order of <hi>S. Francis,</hi> of her acquaintance, ſhe dicouering the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1393:9"/>cauſe of her trauel vnto him, aſſuring him ſhe knew vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that that priſoner was not <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſaying, that ſame priſoner that they cal <hi>D. Sebaſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> king of Portugale had ſent him into Portugal, which ſhe truſted would make wel for that priſoner, and do him no hurt at al: and that ſhe came rather to iuſtifie then to condemne him. The ſame man, my friend promiſed me of particular aduertiſements of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhal be effected in this buſineſſe. I beſeech you conſider the cunning the Caſtilians vſe in the expedition of their enterpriſes, who are both terrible and warie in all their practiſes. Although they know that <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> died in Portugale; yet notwithſtanding they continue their indirect and falſe courſe, with inuentions and ſleights colouring their proiects, to ſeduce and blind the world. This woman a ſubiect of the Spaniſh Kings, was threatned vpon paine of death, not to hinder any of the Kings proceedings; therefore ſhe muſt take vpon her to know this man, and iuſtifie him to be her husband <hi>Marco Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio, &amp;c.</hi> though ſhe had neuer ſeene him before, be the matter neuer ſo falſe, as it is moſt vntrue, and ſo proued by many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and letters whereof I made mention to your Lordſhip in my letters from Florence. I haue ſent a copie to my friend in Rome to be deliuered to his Holineſſe, and another to your Lordſhip with theſe preſents, to controle all thoſe that ſhall belye this action. Beſide this teſtimonie there newly arriued a graue Portugal, a man of good authoritie and credit, that vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding at Rome which way I was departed, tooke poſt horſes &amp; came after me. Beſide that he was one of my old acquaintance, he brought letters in his boſome of recommendation to induce me to truſt him, and that he might open his ſecrets vnto me, which certaine Lords of Portugale (that ſent him) charged him to doe. This man named the houſe in which <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> died, to the owner whereof he brought and deliuered certaine letters from the King, and there were counter letters written which were neuer as yet deliuered to the King. In ſuch ſort, that this falſitie, that this priſoner is <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone,</hi> can by no meanes be proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, in fauour of the inuenters thereof. Now foraſmuch as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1393:10"/>from time to time I am in more liklihood to recouer this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hap: I truſt I ſhall not haue cauſe to ſtay in this towne to write any more letters vnto you, but purpoſe by Gods helpe to make ſmall delay to come my ſelfe to your Lorſhip, and excuſe all other meſſengers. Beſeeching the heauenly King to bleſſe your excellent lordſhip. From Venice the thirteenth of Auguſt. 1601.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Moſt humbly at your excellent Lordſhips ſeruice,</hi> father Fr. IOSEPH TEXERE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The copie of a Letter, written by <hi>D. Raimond Marqueti,</hi> with this inſcription: To <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling himſelfe King of Portugal, being at Venice.</head>
            <p>I Receiued letters from your lordſhip the ſift of September laſt paſt, wherein I perceiue the reſolution your Lordſhip hath taken, to commit your care and truſt to <hi>Marco Tullio Catiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zone,</hi> a man as worthie as able to manage ſuch a buſineſſe. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I render your Lordſhip a thouſand thankes, for the good opinion and confidence you haue repoſed in my perſon; in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of which truſt, I will repaire my diligence, to learne newes of that <hi>Marco Tullio,</hi> who as yet is not returned into theſe quarters. But ſo ſoone as he ſhall, I will giue him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, how ſore your Lordſhip longeth for his returne: and will alſo aduiſe him to execute your commaundements in all points, with exceeding care, diligence, and ſecrecie; and by him I will not faile to giue your Lordſhip to vnderſtand, that when it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth your Lordſhip to ſatisfie your deſire, to ſee this countrey (haiung alreadie runne through the greateſt part of the world) I ſhal procure your conference with theſe noble men, compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to your aduentures which you ſo earneſtly wiſh to behold, viz. the Duke of Aueyro, <hi>Chriſtopher de Tauora,</hi> and the reſt. If you pleaſe to ſend me ſome priuie markes or tokens, that they may repoſe as much confidence in me, as is neceſſarie for the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1393:10"/>diſpatch of your Lordſhips diſſignes in this ſeruice, and any other: I intend to performe to your Lordſhip both diligence and ſecrecie. As for the letter to <hi>Donna Paula Catizzone,</hi> I hold it no policie to deliuer it her, conſidering it is a looſe aduenture in ſuch daungers to truſt a woman. Neither will I neglect to be carefull for the honour of the ſaid <hi>Paula Catizzones</hi> houſe, as your Lordſhip required me: and in the end the effects ſhall ſhew. To conclude, I deſire your Lordſhip to excuſe me for not vſing ſo reuerent a ſtile to your Lordſhip as I could wiſh, which I hope you conceiue I refraine to do, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I would not be diſcouered in your weightier affaires: holding this the beſt and ſafeſt courſe to do your ſeruice: wherein I beſeech the Almightie God to proſper your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and grant you due ſucceſſe, to whoſe tuition with reuerend kiſſing your hands a thouſand times, I commit your Lordſhip. From Meſſina the eighth of October. 1598.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Dom Raimond Marquetl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The copie of a Letter written by <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portugale while he was priſoner in Venice, ſent to Padua to the most reuerend <hi>D. Proſpero Baracco,</hi> Amner to the Cathedrall Church in that towne, the originall remaining in the hands of S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Georgio Buſtarelli.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MOſt reuerend <hi>D. Proſpero,</hi> I am to ſignifie vnto your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, how much I haue bene grieued for your meritleſſe afflictions, hauing ſuffered impriſonment for my ſake, by the pourſuite of the Caſtilians mine enemies. But ſeeing things paſt are irreuocable, and are onely to be ouercome with patience, conſidering you are not ignorant of the whole complotment. And foraſmuch as I am ſo reſtrained from writing at large, that I cannot expreſſe vnto you my ſecret meaning; I onely requeſt you to ſend ſome truſtie meſſenger to Meſſina, diligently to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1393:11"/>and ſearch, whether <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> be returned thither with any directions or not. And to that end &amp; purpoſe, your reuerend Lordſhip may vſe my name to <hi>D. Raimond Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queti,</hi> to whom I wrote heretofore being at Moran, if you forget not, that I receiued alſo anſwer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. And this Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tleman you may informe of all that hath paſt ſince that time (if you thinke good) and when <hi>Catizzone</hi> ſhal happen to come thither, he may direct him couertly to this place, where he may ſecretly giue me knowledge of the expedition in my affaires. And for the loue you owe to the Almightie, faile not one whit in a buſineſſe to me of ſo great importance, conſidering howe much it may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, to bring my long trauailes to good end: and weying, that the Lords of Venice wil not be brought to the true period of iuſtice, notwithſtanding I haue oftentimes labored vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do me right, and make me knowne perſonally to the world, ſaying, that if they finde me not to be <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> king of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, without fauor let them worthily puniſh me. For all this ſute they neither yet would nor will come to the center of my iuſt cauſe, and wrongfull impriſonment, ſaying, that they loued not to be mocked and trifled withall, offering alwayes very rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, that if I would denie, or not profeſſe my ſelfe to be <hi>D. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian &amp;c.</hi> they would ſet me at libertie, &amp;c. Loue me ſtill as I haue done you, &amp; ſo farewel. From Venice the 15. of April 1599.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>D. Sebaſtian King of Portugale.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>Another Letter written by the foreſaid Fr. <hi>Texere</hi> a Portugale, to the ſame Biſhop.</head>
            <p>I Wrote to your excellent Lordſhip fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Venice the thirteenth of Auguſt, and departed thence the eighteenth of the ſame, being then not thoroughly well: for which reaſon I made the way more long and tedious then I purpoſed. I ſtaied many daies at Soleurre, becauſe <hi>Monſieur de Vic</hi> would not let me paſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till <hi>Monſieur de Sillery</hi> came to towne. After whoſe comming
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1393:11"/>he ſtayed me to ſee the order of that Towne, in entertaining the Cantons and other prouincials at their firſt feaſt: and this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement I could not well diſobey. This importunitie and ſuch other were the impediments, that I could not reach vnto Paris before the fourteenth of October. Then preſently I went to Fontaine Bleau, to kiſſe his moſt Chriſtian Maieſties hand; who entertained me verie princely, ſhewing himſelfe glad of my ſafe returne. For to tell you true, I had no aſſured being, but in Fraunce (ſo offenſiue and dangerous was the Spaniſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation vnto me). At my returne from Fontaine Bleau, I met with your Lordſhips Aduocate agent, praying him to giue your Lordſhip aduertiſement of my returne: promiſing to write vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Lordſhip ſhortly after: which I did not effect, partly for mine vnapt diſpoſition, being vexed with ſlaunderous lyes and tales, which mine enemies found occaſion to ſpreade in my abſence. Who for the ſatisfaction of their malice, hauing ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ither care of the law of God, nor of his feare, ſticke not to ſuppreſſe any troth, to further the confuſion of their neighbour, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian brother. And to gorge their wicked appetits, reſpect nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the honor of the King, his ſafetie, nor the fiering of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, which they had lately kindled and diſturbed: and more then that, being blinded in furie themſelues, thinke no man elſe can perceiue their intents, be the matter neuer ſo plaine and manifeſt. But of this theame let this ſuffiſe, conſidering your L. is not ignorant of Caſtilian broiles.</p>
            <p>At my firſt entrance into this place, I found certaine letters written from Rome, Venice, Padua, and other ordinarie paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Italy; all which gaue me credible intelligence, that the King my Lord and maiſter liues, and that he is well intreated, in priſon in the Caſtell De Ouo. And my Romaine friend, being ioyfull of my good newes, wrote vnto me in this forme follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Foraſmuch as your afflictions, daungers, and trauailes haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſome hope of good euent, and for that it is certaine, that the troubles of thoſe that feare God, ſhall be conuerted into proſperitie, ſo it may fall out, that Haec olim meminiſſe iuuabit.</hi> Theſe words and tidings ſeemed very common and vulgar; which being confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with thoſe things that fel out happily in Rome, for the good
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1393:12"/>of my Soueraigne, I conceiued great hope, yet once again to ſee him reeſtabliſhed in his kingdome. By the ſame letter I vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that my intelligence hath bred him great contentment, and that alſo he conceiued no leſſe pleaſure by thoſe copies which I ſent him, to preſent vnto his Highneſſe: which were the tranſcripts of thoſe I ſent your Lordſhip from Venice, which proue that <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> is one, and <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> another. A Doctor and a friend of mine dwelling at Lions, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed me a letter which a French gentleman his inward friend, of good calling dwelling in Rome, after he had recorded many things concerning the King my maiſter, reuealed as followeth. <hi>The Count of Lemos <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy of Naples, is very fauourable to</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>his priſoner, honouring him very much, allowing him ſome ſmall libertie: which when he heard that the King of Castile tooke in ill part, he began preſently to reſtraine and kept him ſporter. When he was allowed to heare Maſſe amongst other priſoners, they did honor him with much reuerence, ſaying among themſelues, that they diſcouered in his countenance and cariage, a princely Maieſtie. And without all queſtion, he must needs be</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>the King of Portugale, or ſome diuell in his likeneſſe. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy (as it is ſaid) craued licence of the King of Caſtil, to go into Spaine, becauſe in Naples he could not recouer his health, which the King would in no wiſe grant him.</hi> There be other letters ſent into theſe parts, not from Portugals, or any other by their appointment, the contents whereof are here expreſſed. <hi>Heretofore it hath bene lawfull and tollerable for this priſoner that termed himſelfe</hi> D. Sebaſtian <hi>King of Portugale, to ſpeake with any Portugals or men of other nations, that deſired to ſee the ſaid priſoner, that ſaid they had ſeene him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: and ſithence they verified him to be</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>the true king of Portugal, he is more ſtraightly kept from the ſight and ſpeech of any then before.</hi> Another letter (hauing recounted ſomething concerning this King) addeth: <hi>The Count Lemos lying in his death bed about the laſt of October, ſaid to his ſonne in the preſence of his wife and diuers other priſoners, that he ſhould looke well to the place and charge he had, both of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroyſhip and his priſoners: for you ſee (ſaid he) that I am vpon the point to go to God, to render account for that I haue done during my life: and here I muſt ceaſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1393:12"/>and end my worldly buſineſſe: for the diſburdening of my ſoule and conſcience, I proteſt that this priſoner here, whom the vulgar call a Calabrian, is the very true</hi> Dom Sebaſtian, <hi>lawfull King of Portugale. I know it aſſuredly, hauing examined him, and for that I haue had often conference with him before his impriſonment. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I commaund and intreat you to vſe him well. This done, he gaue him a letter, which (ſaid he) is written to his Maieſtie, I meane the Catholicke King, touching theſe affaires, and vſe all the diligence you can in theſe things I haue giuen you in charge. The father being dead, the ſonne reſpected the priſoner with much more reuerence then he did before, but allowed him leſſe libertie then he had in the old Counts life.</hi> I haue alſo two letters from Doctor <hi>Sampayo,</hi> the one bearing date the 18 of Nouember, the other the fourth of December, which confirme the ſame contents before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. There be many other letters here lately ſent from Portugals to the ſame purpoſe, reinforcing the truth: and here lately paſt a Portugall by this towne, that proteſteth he ſpake with <hi>Dom Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian,</hi> declaring markes and tokens of his apparell, chamber, and bed, and other appertenances. The ſame Portugall ſaid fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King inquired of him for certaine perſons, which this partie being then but yong, could not remember, and therefore gaue him no direct anſwer. We haue here many rumours from diuers places neare about. One wrote out of Portugale, which diuers other comming from thence confirme, that vpon <hi>S. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonies</hi> day of Padua the laſt yeare, they rong the great bell at Villila in Arragone in the city of Coimbre, an vniuerſity of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, where befell a very admirable and rare wonder. In the ſame towne there is a couent of Canons regulars, of the order of <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> ſincerely reformed, great and rich, in the which is interred the bodie of <hi>D. Alphonſe Henriques,</hi> the firſt King of Portugale, whom they adore for a Saint. In whoſe behalfe (they ſay) God hath ſhewed ſome miracles vnto men, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme their opinion of him, that they beleeue not amiſſe. Many religious men for this foure hundred yeares ſpace ſucceſſiuely continuing this Saint for their interceſſor to God, <hi>(vt ferunt)</hi> haue obtained much releaſe and conſolation in their afflictions, aſwel ſtrangers as the naturall countrimen; and to this effect they haue a booke
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1393:13"/>written, recording all the benefits receiued thereby: ſo that this houſe neuer harboured any other, then thoſe that were deuoted to this holy King. The laſt yeare an old man (whom age had made feeble and decrepit) vſed euer to kneele down and pray at the ſepulcher of the ſaid King: and vpon S. <hi>Anthonies</hi> day the laſt yeare, he there in happie time offered his ſolemne prayers, and continued a long time in meditation before the ſepulcher, where he remained vntill he was ſtiffe, and not able of him ſelfe to riſe, but by the aſſiſtance of his iuniors and religious brethren, who beholding all his face bedeawed with teares, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of him how it came to paſſe. This old man anſwered, I am very much diſpleaſed and grieued at the negligence of our Kings and Princes of Portugale, aſwell dead as liuing, I meane deſcending from this holy King, that being aſſured by infinite miracles that he is in heauen in eternall glorie, and liues in the preſence of God, and we neuer yet knew any man that trauelled to canonize him. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one or two anſwered, That houre ſhal come. And father, ſeeing your deuotion and loue is ſo great to this holy King, beſeech him to be a mediator for the libertie of <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> (deſcending of his maſculine line) that he may be reſtored to his former dignities and Realmes; and that good deed will cauſe him to be canonized.</p>
            <p>We haue heard lately more reports by the paſſengers from Italy and France, that he whom the Venetians impriſoned and releaſed the laſt yeare, is <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> our true King and Lord, and that he ſeemes no whit to degenerate from the ſteps and traces of his aunceſtors.</p>
            <p>As thoſe religious men were aduiſing and contemplating vpon the viſion of this <hi>Alphonſe,</hi> which was mentioned in the <hi>Admirable aduenture, &amp;c.</hi> and conſidering the promiſe God made vnto him, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he appeared vnto him in the field Orique, the ſepulcher reſounded vnto them three ſtrokes, hearing the ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho with abilitie to iudge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the noiſe came. The ſound being paſt, they approched nearer vnto the tombe, continuing their diſcourſe; and ſodainly againe the tombe gaue three other great blows, ſo terrible that they were forced to recule for feare, and the eccho continued ſo long that they all were amazed, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1393:13"/>became as pale and wan, as men vſe to be in the horror of death. When afterward they came to themſelues, recouering their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and perfect vnderſtanding, and conceiued that it came by the old mans praier, they went and reuealed this accident to the Biſhop of that citie who in all the time of treatie betweene Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale and the King of Caſtile, approoued himſelfe as ranke a traitor to his countrey, as he proued true ſeruant to the King of Spaine: who for his recompence was eſtabliſhed in that ſea, and created Biſhop of Coimbre, Count of Arganill, &amp;c. with 50000 duckets of yearely annuitie. This Biſhop aduertiſed of the noiſe, came to the Couent and made inquiſition, and finding it a thing ſo extraordinary, ſaid: You Portugals that wonder at theſe toies, and giue credite to bables, know that the ſoule of this Saint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aloft in glory, is ſo ſore offended with you, that God ſuffereth theſe ſenſleſſe monuments, to giue teſtimonie of your fopperies. Theſe words were ſo ill taken by the people of the town aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about that ſtrange noiſe, that the Biſhop was conſtrained to vnſay that he had ſaid, and to confeſſe it was very wonderfull.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, there are many letters come of late from Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, that teſtifie, that at Lisbone the laſt of October in the yeare 1601. the Church and hoſpitall of the King, (called all Saints) ſodainly fell on fire by night, and flamed ſo furiouſly, that the roofe was burnt, and all the images of the Kings of Portugal that were painted vpon the wall (only the pourtrait of <hi>D. Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>) was left vndefaced. The ſelfe ſame ruine happened to the armes of the Kings and Princes of Portugal, which were drawn in ſcutchions vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wall. The day following being the feaſt of all Saints, in the forenoone fell an infinite number of hailſtones as big as ſmall egges, red of colour, which bred as great cauſe of wonder, as the raine that fell the day following, which was ſo extreme, that (as I haue heard credibly reported by many) the people of that towne durſt not go out of their doores all that day, for ſeare of drowning. Theſe things to me (aſwell as to others) I aſſure your Lordſhip ſeeme maruellous, and can find no reaſon of their rareneſſe: God of his diuine mercie turne them to good. I could haue written to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more newes of great conſequence, if my paper had not bin
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1393:14"/>iniurious. But now to returne to our firſt ſubiect, which I wil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely deliuer vnto your Lordſhip, &amp; ſeeing I haue recouered my ſtrength, I will proceed to declare vnto you the ſucceſſe of <hi>D. Sebastian</hi> King of Portugale, ſince his eſcape from the battell in Afrike: which I intreat your Lordſhip to cauſe to be imprinted, that all Princes may haue free knowledge of the hiſtorie. Paris the twelfth of Ianuarie 1602.</p>
            <p>Immediatly after my laſt writing, I receiued letters from my friends at Venice and Padua, by which I vnderſtand, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of that ſigniorie (being reſident in the Catholicke Kings Court) hath written a letter to that State, which hath bin ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly read at Pregay, part of the contents whereof are: <hi>That the Count Lemos <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy of Naples, before his death wrote a letter to the King his maiſter, wherein he did aſſure him, that that priſoner which he cauſed to be ſent him from the Duke of Tuſcane, vnder the name and title of a Calabrian, was</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>the very true King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, which in the yeare</hi> 1578. <hi>loſt the battell in Africke: which he affirmed with many aſſured reaſons, and trials as hauing throughly examined him of diuers things wherein he had dealt with him both in Portugale and Castile. This <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy neuer receiued anſwer of this letter, in his life: and therefore (being then almoſt at the last gaspe) for the diſburdening of his ſoule, he detected this ſecret to his ſonne that ſucceeds in his place, in the preſence of his wife, his confeſſour, and diuers other perſons of good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, giuing him alſo a letter for the King, wherein is ratified the ſame he ſpake before. The new Viceroy ſent to the Catholike king, a noble man of the houſe of Manriques; of whoſe houſe proceeded the Dukes of Najara. This Siegnior he ſent with his fathers letter, &amp; it is reported that the King returned anſwer of the ſame letter to the Count Lemos, commaunding him to intreate that priſoner well, and take eſpecial care that no diſaſter chanced vnto him.</hi> Theſe news in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced me to inlarge this treatiſe, I would to God they were like to be true, and that the Catholike King would anſwer his title with due correſponde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy to Chriſtianitie, according to his Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſtile, by yeelding libertie to his Coſin-germaine, and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all that to him belongeth: which were an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t branch of honour and magnanimitie, and an aſſured meane to ſettle Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1393:14"/>in peace, and to auoide the daunger of preſent warre, which now the lowring heauens, and malicious inclination of ſtarres do aſſure vs to fall vpon vs. I confeſſe, that ſo many extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary accidents do perſwade me to expect a good iſſue out of all theſe troubles, that may be both happie and profitable to the whole common-weale of Chriſtendome. Pleaſeth it your Lordſhip to remember that about the infancie of our amitie, I ſaid that if the Portugals and the Caſtilians be not ſeparated, it will be impoſſible to maintaine a generall peace in Europe: iuſtifying my opinion, with many euident demonſtrations, and yet to this day I hold the ſame reſolution, in which many noble men both of the counſell and others of great calling do accord, ſaying, They from day to day ſee more apparant reaſons ſo to iudge. To that end do I dayly offer vp my ſacrifices and earneſt prayers to intreate the Almightie God, that it may pleaſe him of his diuine mercie, to inſpire the hearts of all Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to combine in one knot to ſet this cauſe aright, before the increaſe of more miſchiefe: for, ſo much the longer as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre this good worke, ſo much the greater will be the ruine of Portugale, and perill of our vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall deſtruction.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your noble Lordſhips humble ſeruant,</hi> Fr. IOSEPH TEXERE Portugueze.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:1393:15"/>
            <head>A NARRATION OF THINGS DONE BY DOM SEBASTIAN KING OF PORTVGAL, ſince the battell he loſt in the fields of Alquiber in Africke, fighting againſt <hi>Muley Maluco</hi> an Infidell, anno 1578. vntill this preſent time.</head>
            <byline>Written by Fr. <hi>Ioſeph Texere</hi> Portugueze.</byline>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The Preface.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, foraſmuch as I haue done you the fauour by my trauell to diſcouer in writing vnto you a Peregrination ſo much deſired: I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate the like of you againe, in giuing credite to that I will moſt faithfully deliuer vnto you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the naturall inclination of the Portugals, and the diſpoſition of the King.</p>
               <p>The Portugals haue two eſpeciall qualities, happily differing from other nations, which are as familiar to them, as to laugh is proper to all men. The firſt is, they are extremely ſcrupulous of conſcience: the ſecond, they are exceeding conſtant in their reſolutions, eſpecially when they are aſſured that they are warranted by the law of God, and concerne his glorie: for the firſt I will recommend vnto your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments two examples. The firſt, after the death of <hi>D. Henry</hi> ſuppoſed King of Portugale, the ſucceſſion of that kingdome being left to the inheritance of women, came directly to <hi>D. Katherine</hi> Ducheſſe of Bragance, daughter to the ſonne of <hi>D. Duarte,</hi> brother germaine to the ſaid <hi>Henry:</hi> who cauſed her title to be diſputed of in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of Coimbre, which diſputation was publiſhed in print, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1393:15"/>compiled in a booke confirmed by the hands of foureteene Doctours, ſubſcribing thereunto: all whoſe ſentences were pronounced in the fauour of the ſaid <hi>Katherine.</hi> The like cenſure was exhibited by the Doctors of Bologne, Piſa, &amp; other vniuerſities in that part of Europe, the ſucceſſion of the ſaid Realme of Portugale, being adiudged to the ſame <hi>Katherine,</hi> &amp; <hi>D. Iohn</hi> Duke of Bragance, her husba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; coſin germaine: by reaſon whereof (while the Cardinal liued being induced, or rather informed by the Agents of <hi>D. Philip</hi> the ſecond King of Caſtile, not to publiſh the ſaid <hi>D. Katherine</hi> to be his heire, did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite the publication, pretending that <hi>D. Katherine, D. Anthonie,</hi> and <hi>D. Philippo,</hi> being all at once with other competitours to the crowne, might ſet ſome variance among the people about the title, leauing it to be cenſured after his death by certaine Iudges that he had appoined and named) he ſware to ſtand to the ſentence of thoſe Iudges, and would not pronounce him King of Portugale him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but ſaid it might be a meanes for him to come to the beſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the enterpriſe before any other: for that he had on his part, not onely the moſt of the Princes of Portugale, deſcending from that line, but alſo many cities and townes in that Realme, whereof he was owner and Lord, being aboue fifty with caſtles, beſide the citie of Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, and had vnder his gouernement aboue two hundred thouſand ſubiects of account, by reaſon whereof he was the greateſt and the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt Prince ſubiect, among the Chriſtian Princes of Europe. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering withall, that out of the citie of Bragance, and two other townes called Chaues, which the Romaines termed <hi>AEquas Flauas,</hi> he was able to make, and bring into the field thirtie thouſand men, betweene the age of fiue and twentie and fiftie yeares. And it is to be noted, that the men bred in thoſe parts be hard and valiant ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and haue bene ſo approued in the battels and victories which the Portugals haue had againſt the Spaniards, by whom they haue bene often vanquiſhed in ranged battels. This Princes nice conſcience, was the cauſe why he extended not his force to defend his right, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew himſelfe into a corner, without purpoſe or intent to marrie ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther one or the other: by which means he left the crowne to him in the right of his late wife, and his life in ſhort time after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="example">
               <head>The ſecond example.</head>
               <p>The Lord <hi>D. Antonio,</hi> the Prior of Crato, likewiſe ſuppoſed king
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1393:16"/>of Portugale, by reaſon of his oath at Santaren, where he was choſen, and after at Liſbone, in which election he was confirmed by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties of the cities and townes of the kingdome, promiſed by oath that he would make no bargaine or agreement with any of their enemies, but leaue. the ſame Realme at libertie. The Catholicke King <hi>D. Philippo</hi> offered to make him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iceroy of Naples for his life time, with foure hundred thouſand duckets of yearely rent, and the beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of certaine offices and benefites, and fiftie thouſand duckets pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to pay his debts to go into Italy: and likewiſe to reſtore to their former ſtate, dignitie, houſes, and goods, thoſe perſons from whom they haue bene confiſcated by his occaſion, and to giue both ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and riches to all them that ſhould accompanie and attend vpon him, according to euery mans place and calling; vpon condition he would renounce and diſclaime all his right and intereſt in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Portugale, by vertue of their election: and if withal he would ſweare neuer to giue attention to any, that might perſwade him to the contrary. His anſwer was to all theſe great offers: That his conſcience bound him to do nothing preiudiciall to the contract he had alreadie made, and that he had rather liue poorely and die miſerably in a ſimple chamber with credite, performing the dutie of a good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, then to liue in great pompe and pride, in ſumptuous pallaces, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the law and commaundements of God.</p>
               <p>Courteous Reader, no man can ſpeake ſo aſſuredly, or ſo ſenſibly in this matter as I: for in the yeare <hi>1582.</hi> vpon <hi>S. Auguſtines</hi> day, being priſoner at Liſbone, <hi>D. Chriſtopher de Nora</hi> (for that time appointed Viceroy of Portugal, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Catholike M. ſent a gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his chamber for me) aſſured me, that I might talke with him as boldly as with himſelf, telling me that the king meant to employ me to <hi>D. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi> about theſe affaires. This was not then effected, for that I eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped out of priſon: ſince when, in this country &amp; in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, I conferred with him diuers times about this buſineſſe being his confeſſor, who often ſaid vnto me, God forbid I ſhould do a thing ſo contrarie to my conſcience: if I ſhould (ſaid he) I perſwade my ſelfe that euery chinke or furrow in the ground would open and ſwallow me vp preſently, by reaſon of that offence. God firſt I deſire, to take away my life: I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liue laden with afflictions, accompanied with miſerie and begga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, reſeruing my ſerious and publike promiſe, then to leade a periured
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1393:16"/>life in great proſperitie, pleaſures, and delights. Thus he died, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (as I thinke) for the preſeruation of his integritie, aſwell reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among Chriſtian men, as recompence at Gods hand, deſiring al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to liue and reſt in peace: and in regard of his ſmall ambition, could haue contented himſelfe with the tenth part of the King his coſins offer, had it not bene for the reſpect to his oath at their election: and could haue found in his heart, to haue quit the right and claime he had by his father, while the right was in him, but could not dispenſe with the oath they bound him with when they elected him, hauing power to do the firſt, but not the ſecond.</p>
               <p>This is ſufficient (as I take it gentle Reader) to proue vnto you my firſt propoſition, That the Portugals dwell vpon the ſeueritie of their conſcience. Now comming to proue the ſecond, which is, That they are moſt conſtant in their deſignes, when they reſolue to build vpon the true law of God, and his honour, I am to intreate you to defend me againſt the murmurers, our enemies in two reſpects: that is to ſay, not onely in the principall point that ſhall concerne our ſubiect, but that they may become cenſurers of me and of the cauſe, ſaying, That in the firſt hiſtorie of two, I ſpake not religiouſly, and that I giue cauſe of offence to the Kings and Princes of Europe, or that I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite you to take armes againſt them. To the firſt obiection I anſwer, that when a perſon of what eſtate ſoeuer he be, deliuer any thing to good purpoſe, or vtter by chance that which is come to paſſe; in that he offends not, being thereunto obliged in dutie and conſcience. As for the ſecond, where they ſuggeſt that I tranſgreſſe againſt Chriſtian Princes, they are much deceiued: for though a man make fine gold into a chaine, yet for all that it looſeth neither the beautie nor reputation of gold, nor the name of the moſt excellent metall of all others: ſo let it be ſuppoſed that a man deſcended of a prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly race, become a meane ſubiect, yet cannot any man ſay, he looſeth by his deiection of fortune his Nobilitie that came by nature: for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids</hi> ſheepe-hooke was no diſgrace to the Scepter of Iuda, nor <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> wallet, nor the halter of <hi>Gratian</hi> father to <hi>Valentine,</hi> were any blemiſh to the imperiall Crowne. Therefore I conclude, that no man can accuſe me of raſhneſſe in the narration of my hiſtorie, ſpeaking to a good end accidentally, though I proue that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie Kings and Princes of Europe, haue bene deriued out of meane
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1393:17"/>or vulgar houſes.</p>
               <p>The Chronicles of Portugale offer vnto vs among the traditions of our aunceſtors, a notable hiſtorie well worthie the reporting and obſeruing. In Portugale in the Prouince of Alentejo, otherwiſe called Tranſtagana, there is a towne called <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eyros, by eſtimation about the bigneſſe of Manto vpon Seine, ſituate vpon a mountaine, at the foote whereof Weſtward, there runnes a riuer which hath the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the North part, the current paſſing into the South. Not far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that town vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the higheſt part of a litle mountaine, regarding the Weſt for the moſt part, this riuer ſeemes to haue an iſſue towards the Eaſt; and there is a foord where men are conſtrained to paſſe, vnder this promontorie: the riuer hath made a ſandy ſhallow place, as it were knee-deepe, where the women inhabiting the ſaid towne vſe to waſh their linnen, maides aſwell noble as vulgar. It fell out vpon a day that <hi>D. Iohn</hi> naturall ſonne to the King of Portugale, was to paſſe by that point with <hi>D. Petro</hi> Iuſticier &amp; great Maiſter ouerſeer of the cities, and by reaſon of that office was indued with ſpirituall and temporall honour and authoritie. He being a yong and luſtie gallant, and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the ſame towne, beholding theſe maidens with their clothes truſt vp as women vſe going about that labour, this noble man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to ieaſt with the reſt of his companie at the bare-legged wenches, and paſſing by them, ſome part of his traine yet to come, one wench a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the reſt (as the hiſtorie reporteth) in a red peticote, as ſhe was tucking vp her clothes, diſcouered her legs ſomewhat high, and giuing her ſelfe a clap with her hand on the calfe of her right leg, ſaid aloud, Here is a white leg (girles) for the maſter of Auiz. Which being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by ſome of his followers, whom ſhe tooke no heed of, hearing and ſeeing what the wench had both ſaid and done, came no ſooner into their Lords lodging, but they reported vnto him what they had heard a young frolike wench ſay, and ſeene her do. Wherewithall this noble gallant being ſtirred, ſent for her preſently, and finding meanes to haue her ſecretly, vpon her begot a ſonne. And this maide was a ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers daughter of that town, very rich and of good account, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding that his daughter was ſent for to ſuch a noble man, and being informed that her owne ſpeech and light behauior was the firſt cauſe, and being aſſured ſhe was defloured by her owne franke conſent: took it ſo hainouſly, that at her return home, he reuiled her with moſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1393:17"/>opprobrious and deſpitefull words, and beate her out of his doores o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly: and to manifeſt vnto the world, how much he was inwardly vexed with the ſpoile of his daughter, he neuer after would eate at any table, nor ſleepe in a bed, nor put on any ſhirt, neuer pared his nails, pol'd his haire, nor cut his beard, which grew ſo long, that the people called him <hi>Barbadon,</hi> for it continued vncut till it reached beneath his knees. This malcontent liued ſo long that his grand child, called <hi>D. Alphonſe</hi> grew to be a man, and Duke of Bragance (created by the great <hi>Auize</hi> maiſter his father who by the election of the people, afterward became King of Portugale, and for his worthie acts, was ſurnamed memorable) and <hi>Barcelos</hi> by the right of his wife, the ſole daughter, and inheritor to the Conſtable of Portugale. This towne of Veyros, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds betweene <hi>7</hi> or <hi>8</hi> other towns belonging to the ſaid Duke and is diſtant but foure leagues from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>illa Vicoſa, where his pallace is. This vicinitie was the cauſe that he had perfect intelligence of the ſhoomaker his grandfather, &amp; the reports he heard of him, made him ſo deſirous to ſee him, that he determined to go ſeeke him out himſelf in his owne town: where meeting him in the ſtreets, he alighted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his horſe, and kneeled downe before him bare-headed, and deſired him to giue him his hand and his bleſſing withall. The ſhoomaker hauing an eye to the Dukes traine that attended vpon him, and ſeeing his baſe humbleneſſe, and hearing his ſpeeches, amazedly conceiued him to be ſome great perſonage, vnknowne to him, ſaid: Sir, do you mocke me? The Duke anſwered, So God help me I do not: but in earneſt I craue I may kiſſe your hand, and receiue your bleſſing, for I am your grand child, and ſonne to <hi>Ines</hi> your daughter, conceiued by the King my Lord and father. Aſſoone as the ſhoomaker heard theſe ſayings, he clapped his hand before his eyes, and ſaid: God bleſſe me from euer beholding the ſoone of ſo wicked a daughter, as mine was. Yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as you are not guiltie of her offence, hold, take my hand and my bleſſing, In the name of the father, &amp;c. But neither the Duke nor his followers could perſwade him to pull away the hand that couered his eyes, ſo confident this old man was in his diſcontentment: neither would he talke any longer with the Duke. Shortly after, this old man died, and before his death, he tooke order for a tombe to couer him, whereupon he communded to be ingrauen all manner of tooles that belonged to a ſhoomaker, with this Epitaph.</p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:1393:18"/>
               <q>
                  <l>This ſepulcher <hi>Barbadon</hi> cauſed to be made</l>
                  <l>(Being of Veyros, a ſhoomaker by his trade)</l>
                  <l>For himſelfe, and the reſt of his race,</l>
                  <l>Excepting his daughter <hi>Ines</hi> in any caſe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I haue heard it reported by the ancienteſt perſons, that the fourth Duke of Bragance, <hi>D. Iames</hi> ſoone to <hi>Donna Iſabel</hi> (ſister to the king, <hi>D. Emmanuel</hi>) cauſed that tombe to be defaced, being the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of his fourth grandfather.</p>
               <p>As for the daughter, after ſhe was deliuered of that ſon, continued a very chast and vertuous woman all her life, and the king made her Commandreſſe of Santos, a moſt honorable place, and very plentiful (to the which none but Princeſſes are admitted, liuing as it were Abbeſſes and Princeſſes of a Monaſtery, builded without the walles of Liſbone, called Santos (that is, Saints) founded by reaſon of ſome Martyrs that were there martyred. And the religious women of that place haue libertie to marrie with the Knights of their order, before they enter into that holy profeſſion: the order is called <hi>S. Iames,</hi> bearing the ſame Croſſe. In this Monaſterie the ſame <hi>Donna Ines</hi> died, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing behind her a glorious reputation for her vertue and holineſſe. Obſerue (gentle Reader) the conſtancie that this Portugale, a ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker continued in, lothing to behold the honourable eſtate of his grand child, nor would any more acknowledge his daughter, hauing bene a leud woman, ſo purchaſing aduancement with diſhonour. This conſidered, you will not wonder at the Count <hi>Iulian,</hi> that plagued Spaine, and executed the King <hi>Rodrico</hi> for forcing his daughter <hi>la Caua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The example of this ſhoomaker is eſpecially worthie the noting, and deeply to be conſidered: for beſide that it makes good our aſſertion, it teaches the higher not to diſdaine the lower, as long as they be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and louers of honour. It may be, that this old man for his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie riſing from a vertuous zeale, merited, that a daughter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming by deſcent from his grand child ſhould be made Queene of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtile, and the mother of great <hi>Iſabell</hi> grandmother to two Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, and <hi>Ferdinando;</hi> and confute the prouerbe in Spaine:
<q>
                     <l>De cien en cien an<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>os los Reyes villanos:</l>
                     <l>Y de ciento en ſeyes los villanos Reyes. <hi>which is,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:1393:18"/>From a hundred to a hundred yeares Kings become villains: and from a hundred to ſixe, villaines become Kings: ſo here the plough was conuerted into the Scepter, in leſſe then three ſcore and ten yeares.</p>
               <p>For the proofe of my ſecond propoſition, I muſt neceſſarily referre you to the hiſtorie expreſſed in the diſcourſe of the twelfth letter, inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled: <hi>Admirable aduentures, &amp;c. concerning</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>the true and lawfull King of Portugale:</hi> where it is reported of <hi>D. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſe</hi> the African (King of Portugale) that ſeeing King <hi>Lewis</hi> the ſixt deluded him, in not giuing him aid according to his promiſe made at the beginning, when he firſt arriued in France (by which meanes for two yeares ſpace he left Portugal, not being able for want of power to bring his purpoſe to any good paſſe, for his rteurne, being aſhamed to be ſeene of the Portugals, for that he loſt a battell againſt the Caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians) determined with himſelfe to ſteale as vnknowne out of France ſecretly, and place himſelfe in a Monaſtery neare vnto Rome. And to effect that diſſigne he diſguiſed himſelfe in a ſtrange habite, taking with him but two of his people to accompanie him: but he and they were intercepted and taken by the way by <hi>Robinet</hi> (termed the Oxe of Normandy): which <hi>Philippus Comineus</hi> alſo confirmeth with this addition, that king <hi>Lewis</hi> was much offended with <hi>Robinet</hi> for that peece of ſeruice: forcing him to ſupply him with an armie &amp; embark him for Portugale, where he ended his life, as I haue already more at large declared vnto you elſewhere.</p>
               <p>That which I haue ſaid (gentle Reader) I thinke to be ſufficient, to acquaint you with the naturall diſpoſition of Portugales. And to induce you to beleeue what likewiſe hath bin verified concerning <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> my Lord and Maiſter, it is conuenient for you to know, that he reſolued neuer to diſcouer himſelfe, or to make it apparant to any man, what he was; but was fully perſwaded to paſſe the reſt of his time vncothly, and ſo to finiſh his life in ſilence: becauſe he wilfully tooke vpon him (contrary to the aduice of <hi>Xariſa,</hi> and all the Princes, Lords, and Commaunders that accompanied him, to giue battell to <hi>Muley Maluco,</hi> in the houre, the day and place, that in their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was not thought fit for his aduantage: and the King acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his error and ouerſight he committed that day, ſo afflicted his ſoule, that the memorie thereof bred him more inward torment and vexation, then any misfortune that euer befell him in all his wofull
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1393:19"/>dayes. For the confirmation whereof, I will giue you to vnderſtand (courteous Reader) what I heard an old man ſay, being a man of great authority, an ordinary aſſiſtant, and a common releeuer of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted perſons be they neuer ſo abiect, and a Religious man of mine owne Order, and Archbiſhop of Spalato, a Venetian borne, a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer and ſupporter of truth; who during this Realmes laſt troubles, wrote in the behalf of his Chriſtian Maieſtie. This reuerend Prelat, while I lay ficke in his houſe, distant ſome halfe league from Venice, ſitting by my bed ſide, ſaid vnto me: In this very ſelfe ſame bed lay <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> your King, tormented with a feauer, before his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice, at which time in my hearing, a father of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derof <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> a Doctor in Diuinitie, very famous for his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, intreated him to tell him how it came to paſſe that he loſt the battell in Africa: and becauſe the King condeſcended not to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, he reiterated the ſame againe. Then ſuddenly I beheld teares guſhing from his eyes as big as peaſe, and in ſuch abundance, as they did wet not onely his handkercher, but his ſhirt, the ſheete, and a ſilke quilt that laye vpon him. This paſſion was without weeping or ſobbing, for that he neuer could do, but euer ſhewed himſelfe all one, no changeling, come proſperity or aduerſity. At length he requeſted vs inſtantly, to vſe ſome other communication, ſaying, The remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of that intollerable miſhap, was to him ſuch a torment, as it depriued him of reaſon and iudgement, and made him deſire to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don both the ſight and conuerſation of all men. All this griefe could not ſupplant his ſickneſſe, which perſecuted him ſo ſore, as he was out of hope or care of his recouery: oft te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pting him to end his miſery with his owne hands. I conſidered it was great inhumanity to adde a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his affliction, in ſeeking to extract that from his knowledge, which his extreme ſorow would not giue his tong leaue to vtter: ſo I deſired the noble man to depart with me, and giue him time to reſt a while: for that the night before he had ſlept very little or not at all. To conclude, the ſhame and griefe he ſuſtained inwardly by his raſh attempt, as is before rehearſed, committing ſo great an error, and ſo preiudiciall to Chriſtianitie, enforced him to obſcure and hide him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from all his acquaintance and familiars: imitating <hi>Alphonſo</hi> his predeceſſor, both in temeritie and repentance: or to equall <hi>Boleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> king of Poland, who to kill <hi>Staniſlaus</hi> the Biſhop of Cracouia,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1393:19"/>left both his Crowne and Scepter, and retired himſelfe into Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, where ſome ſay within few yeares after the execution of his blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die purpoſe, he ſlue himſelfe. Others ſay, that he was deuoured with dogs in a foreſt: but the moſt certaine report ſaith, that he ſerued a Cooke in a Monaſterie at Carinthia (called <hi>Oſia</hi>) a litle diſtant from the towne named Felikirchen: and after the ſufferance of many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and trauels he died, and was knowne by a writing which was found in his boſome, the content whereof was: <hi>I am</hi> Boliſlaus <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time King of Poland, that ſlue</hi> Staniſlaus <hi>Biſhop of Cracouia.</hi> In the ſame maner I beleeue had <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the King of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale died, had he not bene a religious man, bound in conſcience to ſhew and reueale himſelf, and take paines to ſeeke to be reſtored to his former rights and dignities, ſo prouoked to do by ſecret illumination from God himſelfe, who otherwiſe had reſolued to end his life in an hermitage: which intent he manifeſted in certaine Italian verſes compoſed by him while he was in priſon in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice, which I haue about me, vttering all his ſucceſſe ſithence he loſt the battell in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frike, &amp;c. There were foure examiners appointed by the Senate to attend that buſineſſe all the time of his impriſonment there, which examinations and verſes he ſent incloſed in a letter to his Holineſſe, which alſo are in cuſtodie. The Aduocate, Iudge, Counſellor, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitor testifie, that he gaue them a princely, ſententious, and a pithie anſwer, rehearſing all things that had paſt concerning himſelfe and others, ſince that battell in Africke, with the names of the Generals, Colonies, Captaines, Lords, and Gentlemen, that accompanied him in that action: the number and the diuerſities of nations, the day, the houre, the ſituation of the place, where it was fought; how and in what manner he eſcaped.</p>
               <p>I am againe to intreat you friendly Reader, to giue credite to that I ſhall report vnto you, and not to meaſure the nature of Portugals by the light and leud diſpoſitions of other nations.</p>
               <p>When I was in England with <hi>D. Antonie,</hi> the putatife King of Portugal, as I told you before, I was ſolicited by Fr. <hi>Diego</hi> of Chaues, a profeſſor of mine owne order, with great importunacie to relinquiſh and giue ouer this S' <hi>D. Antonio,</hi> and incline towards his Catholike Maieſtie, whoſe confeſſor this <hi>Diego</hi> was, and his ſole Gouernor: aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring me, that if I would yeeld to his requeſt, I ſhould be very bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1393:20"/>rewarded; &amp; wrote vnto me moſt confidently, that my entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould not want one mite of <hi>25</hi> or <hi>30000</hi> duckets yearely in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenue to be duely paid, which allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce would not only ſerue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>petently to maintaine me in honorabl eſtate, but I might alſo deduct a ſurplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage therehence, to inrich my kindred and friends withall, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo the king promiſed to prefer &amp; aduance for my ſake, (this Cofeſſor was my mothers coſin-germaine) aſſuring me that all my actions, intents, and purpoſes whatſoeuer, preiudiciall to his Catholike Maieſtie, ſhould be quite buried in obliuion, and no blame for any inuectiues or writings in derogation of his Maieſtie ſhould be once obiected againſt me. And to the end I might the rather yeeld vnto him, he recapitulated all the particular offices and fauours he had performed in my behalfe at the time of my impriſonment; that he purchaſed my deliuerance, &amp; ſaued me from being adiudged to the gallies, and alſo preuented me from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtretched vpon the racke: and further, obtained pardon of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie for <hi>Emanuel Texere</hi> my vnkle, that was condemned to looſe his head; and cauſed all his goods to be reſtored, that were confiſcate, for being in employment with <hi>D. Antonio</hi> againſt the king: and when he could not obtaine a graunt at my hands of that which he demaunded himſelf, he incited my friends and acquaintance to do their vttermoſt, to win me from my conſtant reſolution, hoping in regard of the great diſtance and ſeparation from my countrey, and what by the want and neceſſitie I endured in France, with my aged conſtitution of bodie, I would retire from that place and end my age in Portugal, where I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan my youth: attempting afterward by rating &amp; reuiling to make me recant, when other prouocations would not preuaile. All which intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments mixt with bitter taunts, moued me nothing at all: and at this inſtant if I would vouchſafe acceptance, I might receiue the ſame entertainement before offered. It is not yet two yeares paſt ſithence a very deare friend of mine in this towne preſt me with vehement per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions to returne into Portugale, aſſuring me of as much aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there as I would defire: but God forbid, that euer I ſhould accept it, for I had rather be a poore religious beggar in France, then a great diſcontented Biſhop in Caſtile, or in Portugale: conſidering the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is not it ſelfe, but in bondage, moſt ſeruilly ſubiect to Caſtilian ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie. In this towne a nobleman of France, in the preſence of diuers Princes of the Bloud, accompanied with ſome religious men of mine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1393:20"/>owne order, often perſwaded me to leaue the habit of <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> and betake me to another, aſſuring me in liew therof an Abbey (which he had in his power at that time to giue) &amp; afterward a coue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of <hi>8</hi> or <hi>9</hi> thouſand liuers annuall rent: and to make me capable thereof, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to procure me a diſpenſation from his Holineſſe, to allow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of my preſent habite. All which bountifull proffers could not once moue me to change my ſhape, like a mutable weather-cocke, or an airie Camelion. For if the ſpirit of God forſake me not, I will die as I haue liued, a religious votarie to <hi>S. Dominicke,</hi> and a naturall Portugal: and the ſame bleſſed ſtabilitie poſſeſſe all thoſe that ſeeke and ſpred my reproch and defamation; and to thoſe that make a ſcorne of me, I anſwer nothing, but that I am a true religious Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, of the ſame diſpoſition that other my countrimen be: I meane the godly, vertuous, and loyall Portugals. Neither wil I admit any for my aſſociates in this caſe, but ſuch as be moſt intirely ſincere and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. So I end my preſent narration in the name of God, and purpoſe to proceed to the handling of my promiſed diſcourſe: which, albeit I cannot ſo exacty relate, as I deſire (not being an eye-witnes of all that hath bene done and ſuffered by this miſerable king my Lord and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter) I haue gathered out of the greateſt probabilities and aſſertions of the iuſteſt and honeſteſt, that I could poſſibly learne or vnderſtand, that were able to giue me the beſt intelligence: which diligence I was bound in dutie and conſcience to exerciſe, and am withall inforced by the importunitie of many (meeting me in the towne and field at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery corner) to diſcourſe vnto them my maisters aduentures. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſatisfie them and all the world, and to meete with their tedious inquiſitions, I haue effected this collection, to rid my ſelfe of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to quench their inordinate thirſt after the truth, referring all that can reade, to this and my former diſcourſe of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable aduentures. Farewell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="narration">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:1393:21"/>
               <head>The Narration.</head>
               <p>AT my being in Venice (gentle Reader) I vnderſtood by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, that the opinion conceiued of many, and the rumor commonly ſpred concerning the death of <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the king of Portugal, my Lord and Maiſter, was falſe: and beleeued rather, that their reports were more like to be true, that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the contrarie. For that it was confidently iuſtified by credible perſons, that he was ſeene aliue and ſafe ſince the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell in Africke: namely, by <hi>Cid Albequerine, Emanuell Texer</hi> my Vncle, <hi>N. Murſelo Higuera,</hi> and many other Gentlemen and perſonages of great qualitie and account. He eſcaped by flight among the route, being ſore hurt in his head and in one arme, and paſſed as a priuate man to his ſhips, and was embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued amongſt the remnant of his armie, that ſaued themſelues by flight, as he was forced to do. After a few daies he arriued in Portugale in a towne called <hi>Neu feu de mille fuentes,</hi> neare vnto <hi>S. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incents</hi> Cape, where he refreſhed himſelfe, and ſent for a Chirurgian from Faro: his name I haue forgotten (but well I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member he was reckened excellent in his Art.) There the king ſoiourned, accompanied with the Duke of Aneiro, and <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Tauora,</hi> and diuerſe other Lords, vntill he was perfectly healed. The tidings of his being at the Cape were ſodainly ſpred at Lisbon, and was ſoon publiſhed generally throughout all Portugal. And it was affirmed, that he was ſeene at the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of Capuchins (built vpon the point of <hi>S. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incent</hi>) amongſt his companions. This rumor was ſoone quailed by the policie and authoritie of <hi>Petro de Alcaçoua,</hi> great Secretarie of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, in the behalfe of <hi>Dom Philip</hi> king of Spaine, with whom he had before-hand concluded, when <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the king employed him in Embaſſage into Spaine, before his departure into Africke. And for that cauſe this <hi>Petro Alcaçoua</hi> (a damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Politician and a monſtrous traitour) as ſoone as the firſt newes came, that the Chriſtians had loſt the day, and his King and Maiſter ſlaine, this Iew gaue ſecret intelligence to the king of Caſtill of all that happened: ſignifying vnto him, that nowe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1393:21"/>were a fit time to ſurpriſe the kingdome of Portugall, and bid him make readie for the purpoſe. I reſpected the handling of the ſecond eſtabliſhment of vnion betweene the king my mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter before his departure, and the king of Caſtile, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by one <hi>Conneſtay</hi> at large; who being a man of good reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect in Portugal, came poſt to ſeeke me from Rome to Venice, and amongſt many other newes, he reported vnto me, that as ſoone as euer it was bruted abroad in Portugall, that <hi>Dom Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> the king was liuing, and priſoner in Venice, there were many deuiſes reuiued concerning this brute, that long time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lay buried. And withall you muſt note, that <hi>Dom Diego de Soſa</hi> the Admirall, which conducted the king into Africke, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embarqued him from thence into Portugall againe, and gaue continual intelligence vnto his kindred and aſſured friends, that their king was liuing, and that he had ſecretly receiued him a boord, among the ſcattered troupes, and gaue them an eſpecial charge, that they ſhould conceale it. And further, that he gaue him a ſecret ſigne, whereby he might know him hereafter, if need required: which priuitie, <hi>Dom Diego</hi> diſcouered vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, when a counterfeit (ſuborned for the purpoſe) came to that <hi>Diegoes</hi> houſe, ſending for him into the field to come home to ſpeake with <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the king: to whom he ſaid ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptly: Hath he deliuered any ſecret token betwixt him and me, whereby I might credite thee? By which queſtion he publiſhed that, which he ſecretly had bewrayed before to his allies. Whereupon the Cardinall <hi>Dom Henry,</hi> great Vncle to the king, tooke occaſion to ſend a truſtie ſeruant of his, called <hi>Ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Antunes,</hi> to <hi>S. Vincents</hi> Cape, charging him to vſe all the induſtrie he might, in finding out what certaintie he could learn of the king his Nephew. All which, this <hi>Emanuel</hi> performed, with as much indeuour as he might poſſibly vſe: and by his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent inquiſition about the ſaid Cape, found that the king had bene in the Monaſterie: and was there certified, that he was both hurt in the head and arme, and in a manner franticke, not onely for the exceeding anguiſh and vexation of mind which he ſuffered for the loſſe of victorie, but withall the ſhame did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer perplexe him, when he conſidered the ouerthrow came by
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1393:22"/>indiſcretion and raſhneſſe, and that by his default the flower and prime of all Portugal, was defeated and cut off. <hi>Antunes</hi> brought a very large teſtimoniall hereof to the Cardinall vnder the ſeale of the father Gardian, and all the reſt of his brethren of the ſaid Monaſterie: which the Cardinal receiued with his owne hands, commaunding his ſeruant to impart this ſecret to none, which he for his owne part buried in his own boſome. And not being able to find out what courſe his Nephew and his companie tooke for their eſcape out of the countrie, gaue ouer the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of his recouery either of his crown and ſcepter while he liued, though it were his due. But when it was knowne in Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal that the K. liued, <hi>Antunes</hi> bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to acknowledge the paines he had vndergone in theſe affaires, by his maſters appointment: which was no ſooner conueyed to the king of Caſtiles care, but he ſent for this <hi>Antunes,</hi> of whom he had a liberall relation of all that he knew concerning that buſineſſe: and ſoone after <hi>Antu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> his returne into Portugall, he died. Whereby it appeareth vnto me, that God lengthened his life ſome ſpace, to reueale a truth, that ſeemed before to be very intricate and doubtfull. Shortly after the Portugals began to murmure among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, boldly ſaying, that <hi>D. Philip</hi> the king had made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> their king (his Nephew) going to him to craue his aide before his departure into Africke, becauſe he had a meaning to gaine the kingdome of Portugall to him and his ſucceſſours, and hold it by vſurpation. And this ſcandall was neuer extinguiſhed, becauſe fame diuulged his arriuing at the Cape called <hi>S. Vincent,</hi> and no certainty appeared to the world, what way he paſſed from thence. But ſince it is proued, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spaine he got ſhipping and trauelled into Alexandria, and there liued in <hi>Preſter Iohns</hi> Court with his followers, ſome twentie moneths, vnknowne of what qualitie he was, profeſſing that he had a deſire to ſee the world, and trauelled onely to that end and purpoſe: for of want he made no ſhew, he and his company being well furniſhed with gold and iewels of great price. From Aethiopia they paſſed ouer the red ſea, and ſo directly to the mount Sinay; from thence to the great <hi>Sophi</hi> called <hi>Xatama</hi> king of Perſia, whom he ſerued as a Commaunder fiue or ſixe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1393:22"/>yeares againſt the Turkes, where he atchieued many victories, and diuerſe wounds in his bodie, with much honour and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. In requitall whereof, the king of Perſia did him many honorable offices, and gaue him rich preſents of ineſtimable price, with the which he and his companie departed. I heard at Venice of his conference with Colonel <hi>Cigogna,</hi> a man of great experience in the warres, which aſſured the Lords of the Senat, that he neuer talked with any man more wiſe, learned, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter experienced in Militarie diſcipline, then this noble perſon: and he proteſted he could be no other, then the ſame he profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be. The excellent and moſt reuerend Lord the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſaid, he heard the diſcourſe between the King and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel, which delighted him exceedingly. This Archbiſhop I could not ſpeake withall at my being in Venice, for that he was employed in Dalmatia in the affaires of the State.</p>
               <p>The King leauing Perſia, went towards Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence he trauelled by firme land to Conſtantinople: which after cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine dayes he left, and came into Italie, from thence to Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and from thence fetched a compaſſe by Muſcouie, Poland, Swedland, and Denmarke, where he tooke ſhipping for En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland: and in London it is reported he ſaw <hi>D. Antonio</hi> the ſuppoſed king of Portugal. From England he paſſed into Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; from Holland by Almaine backe to Antwerpe: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence to Paris, <hi>anno</hi> 1586. It comes to my memorie, that in the latter end of the ſame yeare, one <hi>Antonio Fernandes Pignero,</hi> a Prieſt, which had ſometime bene Amner to the ſaid <hi>Dom Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian,</hi> &amp;c. and was with me in ſeruice from the ſaid Lord <hi>D. Antonio,</hi> told me that the ſame <hi>Dom Antonio,</hi> had heard it credibly reported, that <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> the King was liuing, &amp;c. whereat <hi>D. Antonio</hi> ſeemed to be ſore amazed and perplexed. About which time I craued licence of <hi>D. Antonio</hi> to go out of England into this countrie, which he gaue with ſome ſhew of diſcontentment therewith. By reaſon whereof, and to auoid all ſuſpition, I moued no queſtion to him concerning the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laritie of this matter; and I muſt tell you by the way, that <hi>Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero</hi> had all this diſcourſe in writing <hi>ſub ſigillo confeſſionis,</hi> which although (ſaid he) I make the ſame knowne vnto you, yet I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1393:23"/>pray you conceale it from <hi>D. Antonio,</hi> becauſe it may be very preiudiciall to him of whom I heard it. In the yeare follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after Eaſter, in the time of Ember, when I was come to that towne, whither I made the ſcope of my iourney, I heard the like concerning the ſame buſineſſe which I before had heard in England, whereof I ſeemed to make no great care: and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Paris, after his Chriſtian Maieſtie had entred the town, <hi>D. Nouuclet</hi> aſſured me in the preſence of diuers Portugals and French men, not once nor twiſe, but many times, that it was as certaine and aſſured that <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> (King of Portugale) had bene lately in Paris, as he ſpake to me: deſcribing him to me by many circumſtances: to all which I gaue no credite, eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming all he ſaid to be meere fables. Not that I held any opinion or conceit that he was ſlaine at the battell in Africke, but my i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination could not receiue any impreſſion that he could be guiltie of any ſuch rare diſſimulation to paſſe ſo many cities and regions without diſcouerie.</p>
               <p>The laſt yeare writing to the ſaid Doctor to <hi>Anniſſi</hi> where he dwelt, of theſe newes which I heard, that my Lord and maiſter ſhould be ſet a libertie by the conſent of the Siegniorie of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice: I intreated him to write vnto me at large, that which he had oft recited to me in this town, concerning the eſtate of that King. And becauſe his anſwer was, that he could not agree to the ſatisfaction of my demaunds, I ceaſed to importune him any further in that behalfe. But foraſmuch as at my being at Venice, ſome of the chiefeſt of the Siegniorie of that State, asking me if I were able to ſay any thing concerning that the King had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered vpon his examination: ſaying, that he had bene in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, and there conferred with a Portugale fled out of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey for <hi>D. Antonioes</hi> cauſe, being his coſin. And further, that he met with a gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Swiſſer-land at Soleurre, departing from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce towards Anniſſi, by whom I ſent a letter to <hi>D. Nouuelet:</hi> in the which I moſt inſtantly deſired him to ſet downe in writing all that he had declared to me at Paris, concerning my maiſter <hi>D. Sebaſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp;c. At my great importunity it pleaſed him to grant me my deſire, and here I haue annexed the ſame, copied out ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim, as it was written, in maner and forme, with the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1393:23"/>he aſſigned me to do to his friends, (named in the ſame originall) men of good eſteeme for birth, office, and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar affectation. So that to his truth and ſinceritie no man can take exception, being a profeſſor in his art, both very learned and excellently experienced, in his life and manners neuer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected. Therefore all ſuſpition either of the matter or the man is preuented.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The copie of a Letter ſent from <hi>D. Nouuelet</hi> to Fr. <hi>Ioſeph Texere.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIR, I receiued your laſt Letter dated the eighteenth of the moneth paſt: whereby you make me recal to mind the griefe I conceiued by your letters preceding, concerning the troubles of <hi>Emanuell Godigno,</hi> a Gentleman, borne in Portugale. I had long ſince expreſſed in writing, and ſent it you, if I had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your diſpoſition had bene apt to entertaine newes. So ready and willing I am to applie my endeuours to do you ſeruice, in any thing you ſhall pleaſe to commaund me: but the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your rare perfection of memorie, made me decline from doubt of any defect therein, and ſo much the ſlower in commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that to writing, which I had before ſo obſeruantly vttered in your hearing, and in the preſence of many perſons of good reſpect, aſwell of your countrey, as of other nations: imputing this impoſition rather to your deſire to be better aſſured, <hi>Obſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis tabulis,</hi> then to any want of cariage in your vnderſtanding parts, I thus addreſſe my pen to confirme my tongues diſcourſe. In the yeare of our Lord 1588. being at Nance, in emploiment and ſeruice of my Lord the Cardinall of Gondie, about the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of my Lord the Biſhop of Paris, his nephew, that was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Abbot of Buzai; I tooke vp my lodging in the couent of the Iacobins, where I found good oportunitie to ingraft my ſelfe in the fauour and friendſhip of the reuerend father <hi>D. Sampayo,</hi> a man much commended for his liberall erudition in letters, but recommended for his integritie and zeale, one of your owne or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and of your ancient and approued acquaintance, and being
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1393:24"/>both godly and learned, vnited in more aſſured bonds of loue and amitie, then are exerciſed among the vulgar. Meane while that league of friendſhip then planted betweene that good <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Sampayo</hi> and me, tooke ſo good roote in vs both, as it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth without perill of ſupplanting til this day: and is like for your ſake to fructifie aboundantly, as well by increaſe of loue, as of acquaintance with many other noble gentlemen of good ſort and condition. Among the reſt of the ordinary frequenters, came <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Emmanuell Godigno,</hi> to viſite Doctor <hi>Sampayo</hi> at my lodging, and taking ſome acquaintance of me, continued the ſame as long as I lay in Nance: till I retired towards Paris, leauing to my great ſorrow the ſweete conuerſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Doctor <hi>Sampayo</hi> and my ſelfe, louing each other dearely. This <hi>Godigno</hi> loth to let ſlip out of vſe, the complements that had paſt betweene him and me at Nance, at his comming to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris frequented my lodging daily, to vnderſtand of Doctor <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payoes</hi> health and welfare: whereof I not being able to giue him any certaine intelligence, he began to mourne and looke heauily, whom I could not chuſe but in that paſſion to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, enuying any mans affection ſhould exceed mine in zeale to my friend. It followed that, vpon a ſunday (in what moneth I remember not) this <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Godigno</hi> receiued the Communion very deuoutly, miniſtred by the chiefe of the <hi>Iacobins,</hi> which made me refraine for that time to ſalute him, or he me: for intruth I thinke he ſaw me not, and I not willing to interrupt his deuotion, let him paſſe without any ceremonie on my part performed. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the ſame afternoone he repaired to my lodging, and as his cuſtome was, demaunded what tidings I heard of his friend and mine Doctor <hi>Sampayo:</hi> and I hauing no better means to informe him then before, deſired him to excuſe my ignorance being vnable to giue him any contentment by intelligence of him, or from him. At which anſwer, the kind gentleman ſeemed very penſiue and appaled, ſitting ſtill a long while mute and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: whereby I imagined he had ſomwhat that inwardly diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered him, for I might perceiue the teares trickle downe his cheekes. Which perturbation breaking out at his eyes, afforded him ſome libertie to vtter theſe words following: <hi>Sir, I conſider
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1393:24"/>the great loue that was betwixt Doctor</hi> Sampayo <hi>and you, that mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeared to me at Nance: &amp; withal, the confidence he repoſed in your fidelitie towards him; which perſwades me, that I cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a ſecret matter of great conſequence to a man that can more aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly conceale it then your ſelfe. And I doubt not but the ſame ſhall be as ſafely guarded in the treaſurie of your conſtancie, as in his, if you will vouchſafe to giue me your vnfained promiſe ſo to do.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto I anſwered: <hi>Sir, if it be a ſecret neuer as yet by you reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to any man but vnto me, you may boldly ſpeake it: but if you haue alreadie truſted any man, or ſhall hereafter declare the ſame to any other, it may ſo fall out, that you may lay ſome other mans deſerued blame to my charge. Therefore in this doubtfull caſe I beſeech you truſt your ſelfe, and tell me nothing: for I will not haue you ranſacke your incloſure vpon my proteſtation, although I preſume ſo much vpon your honeſt ſinceritie, being a Gentleman both honeſt and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, you wil vtter nothing vnto me, that ſhall not be like your ſelfe: conſidering beſide, I haue ſeene you this day participate a ſound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, moſt reuerently and deuoutly among the Iacobins, which aſſures me, that you cannot produce any thing out of your mouth either pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane or wicked.</hi> Whereunto he replied, that he was expreſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receiue the holy Communion vpon this day, to the end God might inſpire him with the vnderſtanding, what was fitteſt for him to do in this caſe, and reſolued abſolutely to tell it me, that I might diſcloſe it to Doctor <hi>Sampayo,</hi> fearing leaſt he might die, burdened with ſo great a ſecret, as concerned the good of all Chriſtendome, holding his conſcience greatly char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with the weight thereof, coniuring me ſeriouſly to deliuer it ſafe to Doctor <hi>Sampayo:</hi> meane while if it pleaſe God to take him out of this tranſitorie world, it might be lawfull for me to publiſh it openly before my death. This and ſuch other like ſpeeches being ended, he began to vnboſome his conceit, in this manner: It was my chaunce to meete with a Gentleman in this towne, my countriman, betweene the which and me there had bene auncient amitie: after many dayes conference at ſecret meetings, he told me that <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the King of Portugale was not dead: wherat the ſaid <hi>Godigno</hi> ſeemed to be aſtoniſhed, and ſaid, he did not beleeue it, vntil he had ſeene him aliue with
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1393:25"/>his owne eyes, and then (ſaid he) I may haue reaſon to be of your mind. Which the other promiſed ſhould be effected, and to that purpoſe caried him to dinner to the houſe where <hi>Dom Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> was lodged, which was as I remember in S. <hi>Iames</hi> his ſtreete, or in harpe ſtreete; whether the firſt or ſecond day, or ſhortly after he had vſed to that place, he could not certainely name the time, but a friend of his a Portugal came and inquired at the houſe for <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> King of Portugal: and as he was comming vp the ſtayers, <hi>Godigno</hi> haſted downe the ſtayers to ſtop his paſſage, and tooke occaſion to carie away his friend, faining ſome other affaires with him becauſe he would preuent the King from diſcouery, who was very iealous of publicke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. But the morrow after, the ſame gentleman came againe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his former buſineſſe, and inquired earneſtly for the King, and being there denied him, ceaſed not to aske of euery one he met throughout all the citie for <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, but not preuailing at all, he fell into an extreme agonie, and deſiſted not from inquiſition, to litle purpoſe: and ſurpriſed with great care what to do, was at length inſpired with a motion fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God to profeſſe a ſolitarie life, and take vpon him the habit of an hermite: ſo, being diſguiſed trauelled towards Spaine, and arriuing at the Court, made meanes to ſpeake with the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke King, ſaying, that he had matters of great importance to reueale vnto him, and to none but the King. And after long attendance, he was admitted to the Kings preſence to haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, to whom he proteſted he had lately ſeene <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> in Paris, and confirmed it by many ſignes and tokens of veritie. The King preſently forbad him by any meanes to vtter it to any man liuing, and willed him to go abroade euery where to ſearch out and diſcouer what he might poſſibly, allowing him preſent money to beare his charges, deliuering him a letter to <hi>D. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardin Mendoſa,</hi> then his ledger Ambaſſador in France, to giue him any money he ſhould haue cauſe to vſe, not ſignifying vnto him for what cauſe or intent: and thereupon he ſhewed me let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which made the matter euident that he had bene in Spaine, as is aforeſaid; but for the particularities of the ſaid letters I do not well remember, but that I hold my ſelfe ſatisfied thereby
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1393:25"/>that he had bene in Spaine, &amp;c. but to continue his tale, he told he had trauelled ſo long that his money being well waſted he was forced to go to <hi>Mendoſa,</hi> to be ſupplied in his neceſſitie, to whom when he would not reueale the cauſe of his comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe parts, and hauing letters of intelligence out of Spaine from ſome great man that he ſhould deliuer that <hi>Godigno</hi> no more money, being but an impoſtor and a deluder, as they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him, <hi>Mendoſa</hi> was ſoone confirmed in that parſimonie, intending before to ſhut vp his liberalitie and to giue him neuer a deneere: at which deniall this <hi>Godigno</hi> began to lament and burſt forth into bitter teares: as I iudge his lamentation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was croſt and preuented for comming to the type of his enterpriſe.</p>
               <p>In the end, proteſting before God and his Angels, and by vertue of that holy Sacrament he had that day receiued, that all that he had vttered to me was true: in the end without prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of beleeuing or ſhew of incredulitie, I promiſed him my ſecrecie, as he deſired: ſome few daies after this conference, he returned vnto me as he vſed to do inquiring what news I heard of father <hi>Sampayo:</hi> to whom I anſwered, I vnderſtood of him no more then before. Meane while, I was (as it were) diſtracted in conceit, ſeeing this Gentlemans relation a paradoxe aduerſe to the fame and vulgar opinion of <hi>Dom Sebaſtians</hi> death: and wey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Gentlemans integritie, zeale, and communication with the lacobins, could not in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne him for a lier. But whether it were true or falſe, according to my promiſe I concealed it (though it were in ſome ſort an offence ſo to do). It came to paſſe in ſome litle ſpace after, in the houſe of an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie, dwelling in the ſuburbes called <hi>S. Germaine,</hi> neare the gate (whoſe houſe was razed at the ſiege of Paris) that this man died. Here is all that I can ſay concerning this ſubiect, which I neuer opened to any man ſauing to Doctor <hi>Sampayo,</hi> which was a good while after, but the time I do not iuſtly remember: and one cauſe why I was loth to ſpeak of it, was, for that I was afraid to be thought deluded. And me thinks this I haue written vnto you may ſeeme very ſtrange, notwithſtanding the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon report at this houre is, that <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> was ſeene aliue two yeares
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1393:26"/>after he was detained in Venice: but I tell ye, the greater part of the world ſuppoſe, that he is a counterfeit, ſuborned, &amp;c. God knowes what he is, who euer ſend you happie and long life: ſo with my humble recommendations to your reuerend ſelf, I leaue you. From Anniſi the laſt of September, anno 1601.</p>
               <p>I forgot to tell you, that <hi>Emmanuel Godigno</hi> added to that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; that the Catholicke King gaue him in eſpeciall charge to tell <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> that the Catholike King requeſted him by any meanes to haſten his returne without delay to him, deſiring nothing ſo much as to render him the poſſeſſion of his Realme and kingdome, and to beſtow his eldeſt daughter vpon him in mariage.</p>
               <p>I am farther to deſire you of ſo much fauour, as to ſend me theſe bookes from Lions here mentioned in a catalogue inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this letter, and I will faithfully repay whatſoeuer you ſhall lay out to that purpoſe. Here follow the titles: All the workes you can find, <hi>De regno Chriſti temporali.</hi> I beſeech you ſalute for me <hi>Monſieur le Feure,</hi> recommending my faithfull ſeruice vnto him: of whom if it pleaſe you, you may craue aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in my buſineſſe, for he is a man, <hi>multae lectionis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Good Lord! I had forgotten my dutie to <hi>Monſieur de Tyron,</hi> to <hi>Monſieur Pelle jay,</hi> to <hi>Monſieur de Marnay,</hi> and to my louing frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Amboiſe, three brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reckning my ſelf much bound to them all: notwithſtanding, I feare they little trouble them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with the thinking vpon ſo meane a man as my ſelfe, and this conceit halfe diſmaies me to trouble you ſo far as to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me in all humilitie to my Lord Biſhop of Eureux. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer you ſhall thinke conuenient to performe in my behalfe, either to adde or diminiſh, I referre to your diſcretion.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your most humble ſeruant,</hi> CL. D. Nouuelet. <hi>The ſuperſcription.</hi> To M. <hi>Texere</hi> Portugueze, Counſellor and Amner to the King, &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1393:26"/>
               <head>A Declaration.</head>
               <p>THe King <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> departing from Paris trauelled tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Fraunce directly into Italy: and I know not who followed him, or where he forſooke his companie, but moſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured I am, he reſolued to giue ouer the pompe and glorie of the world, and to retire himſelfe to liue priuatly; and being in Dalmatia, he made choiſe of an hermitage for his habitation, contenting him therewith in liew of his former princely palace. This poore hermitage was ſituated on the top of a moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, neare the citie of Leſine, where he abode for the ſpace of three yeares: in the iſſue of which time there arriued a ſhip of Portugale, from whence ſome paſſengers going a pilgrimage to that hermitage, ſeeing the King, knew him incontinently, and ſaid aloud: <hi>Behold, yonder is our King Dom Sebastian;</hi> and ſpread this rumour preſently about the citie. The King perceiuing that he was diſcouered, grew much diſpleaſed therewith, and vpon that diſcontentment, determined with himſelfe to forſake the place, (to the great crucifying of my ſoule, for there he liued in great tranquilitie of mind with no leſſe conſolation) being in a bodily feare leaſt the Portugals ſhould come thither and ſearch for him, he thought good to go: and before he went from Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſine, he diſtributed all his moueables and houſhold-ſtuffe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his friends: three of the which comming to Venice were called before the Senate, before whom they confirmed al which the ſaid King confeſſed vpon his firſt examination touching his eſtate and accidents in thoſe quarters. The Senators called them to come before the King face to face in open view of the whole Senate and aſſiſtants, and they knew one another very well; and one of them brought a picture with him, which the King had left behind him, vpon the which was painted, Ieſus Chriſt crucified, with <hi>S. Sebaſtian</hi> and <hi>S. Anthonie</hi> of Padua. And this act is ſo common in Venice, that they talke thereof without controlement.</p>
               <p>The King departed from Leſine wandring here and there, ſeeking ſome conuenient place to retire himſelfe into, fit for his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1393:27"/>deſigne, lodged himſelfe in a mountaine neare Piſa, where he ſpent his time as you ſhall heare. He had hoſe, and what elſe I know not, but no hat, nor other neceſſary thing that might ſerue inſtead there of: by reaſon whereof you muſt needs imagine his complexion of force muſt alter, which from ſwart became black, his haire grew long, but not vnſeemely, for he vſed to cut it: his garments were of courſe cloth, and his food herbes, rootes and fiſhes, which were giuen him for Gods ſake: he frequented the citie, where, the firſt moneths of his arriuall, he gaue monie towards the dowries and mariages of poore maidens, and at his owne charge deliuered many out of priſon, diſcharging their debts. And hauing diſtributed all he had for God ſake, he was faine to receiue again for God-ſake, and took that in good part which was giuen him in the towne, onely to ſerue the neceſſities of his perſon, which were few, conſidering the auſteritie of his diet and hard penance which he willingly indured, relecuing priſoners with the ſurpluſage of his poore fortunes, if he had any, to whom he did many ſeruices by his trauell &amp; labor, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch their buſines whenſoeuer they requeſted him. One repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto me, that he had many charitable almes at a Portugales houſe in the towne, who miniſtred vnto him clothes and other neceſſaries, without knowledge what he was, or where he was borne: which he by his owne confeſſion tooke very thankfully. The like befell him in <hi>S. Alexis,</hi> where he afterward arriued: and after in Ediſſe a citie in Syria, he receiued bencuolence of his owne ſeruants, that wandred almoſt through the habitable parts of the world to ſeeke him.</p>
               <p>After he had remained certaine yeares in theſe mountaines, there appeared a viſion vnto him by night, wherein he thought God commaunded him to repaire home into his owne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and leaue this deſolate and ſolitarie life, and abandon both hermitage and mountaines: but afterward miſliking his former opinion, he bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuſpect the ſame apparitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall, or meere fantaſticall, and reuoked that purpoſe for to proceed in his iourney homeward: but a very old man dwelling neare vnto him in the foreſaid deſolate place, with whom he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in a great league of amitie, becauſe he was a vertuous man,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1393:27"/>exerciſing himſelf wholy in deuotion and prayer, made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke that vnreuerent conceipt of his viſion, ſaying that it was a good and a godly motion, and therfore could not proceed from an ill ſpirit: and therefore a godly and a diuine viſion, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded him to do his indeuour, to execute that, which therein was giuen him in charge.</p>
               <p>The King liſtened vnto this old mans aduice, and ſo much the rather, for that he diſcouered vnto him before many ſtrange things, and foretold many matters that he had ſeene take euent according to his prediuination. Whereupon the King wiping away the teares from his cheekes, which his wofull heart had ſent outward as meſſengers of ſecret ſorow, tooke his leaue of his fellow in affliction, like one depriued (by griefe) of ready vſe both of reaſon and iudgement. So, abruptly leauing his louing friend and religious companion, trotted onwards of his iourney from one place to another, vntill he came to Meſſine a citie in Cicile. In which place it is ſuppoſed he had left (paſſing that way before) ſome peeces of gold and iewels of value, which to recouer, to ſerue his preſent turne, and to furniſh him in good ſort, he was forced to diſcouer himſelf to his companions, from whom he had ſtolne long before.</p>
               <p>In this voyage he ſent <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> into Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, with diuerſe letters, to many perſons of qualitie (as is ſaid before in my Treatiſe called <hi>Admirable aduentures.</hi>) And at Meſſine he ſhipt himſelfe in a Gally belonging to his Holines, bound for Genua, being fraught with ſilkes, &amp; afterward came to Ciuita Vecchia. From whence without any delay he poſted to Rome, and was lodged neare vnto <hi>S. Peters</hi> Church, where as he was ſleeping in his chamber, he was robbed by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of his ſeruaunts, whom he had newly entertained into his ſeruice, not long after his comming to Rome. And very neare as ſhortly after my departure therehence, hearing of the rumour, I ſent to a friend of mine there, to giue me intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the certainty of theſe tydings. Who ſent me word that he had bene at his lodging, and ſpake with his hoſteſſe, being a widow, and with her children and ſeruants, which reported all that had paſt in that buſineſſe, ſaying they well diſcerned by his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1393:28"/>behauiour, that he was ſome honourable perſonage, or ſome very great Lord, and ſaid they were very much grieued with the infortunate rumour that was ſpread there, that he was declared to be <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the true King of Portugale; which by his grauitie and maieſticall behauior aſſured them no leſſe, then that he was ſome great Prince.</p>
               <p>Conferring this I now learned, with theſe circumſtances col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected before in this countrie, and afterward confirmed at Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, any man may be well aſſured that this report was true. At Venice one ſhewed me an inuentorie, written with his owne hand, of thoſe parcels of treaſure that had bene ſtolne from him: amongſt the reſt there was a chaine of gold garniſhed with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones; which the great Sophi preſented him, with a dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond of great value, and rings with precious ſtones moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitly ſet, with many other peeces of good eſtimation and value. And while he was diſtempered for the loſſe of theſe iewels, he miſt certaine papers, the purports whereof were of great importance: all which were ſlipperily conucyed away; which being kept had bene direct teſtimonies to ſerue his turne, in the doubtfull opinions of them that were to trie and ſift him, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were the ſame <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> he pretended to be. And hauing vnderſtanding of ſome ambuſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t laid to intrap him by the paſſage of Vmbrie, he altered his courſe and went by Narne; and when he came thither, and heard no newes of his enemies in his way, he went forward by Tarne: where he had intelligence that his Holineſſe would go to our Ladies of Laret. Then he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed his iourney to that place directly; and when he came to Neuuaine, he vnderſtood his Holines had changed his purpoſe, and was reſolued to go by Bologne, and ſo to Ferrara: the King after his deuotion ended, bent his trauel towards Bologne. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when he came ſore wearied and tired miſerably, he heard of another alteration, that his Holineſſe by meanes of ſome ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that came vpon him ſo dainly, had no intent once to budge from Rome, being forced to keep his chamber. This toſſing and reeling to no purpoſe, troubled the poore King exceedingly, hauing broken the necke of his deſignes: not knowing then what way to take, thought with himſelf to go ſome way at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1393:28"/>not reſoluing vpon any one, his fortunes grew ſo variable: at the laſt he directly paſt to a village, which belongs to the Count of Verone, in the mid-way to Mantoue, which ſome call Nogara. And when he came to that borough, a ſtrange imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation poſſeſſed him, that one violently withſtood him, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any further that way. Then, he ſuppoſing himſelfe to haue day-light inough to guide him to Mantoue, was contented to be checked in the other paſſage; finding his mind aſſailed with a thouſand variable cogitations, which ſo afflicted him, that he could not vtter any one period of his vexations, to him that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied him. Al this time I had no certain report of the kings being in that place: which is the cauſe I made no mention of the day, as I vſed to do of his other paſſages.</p>
               <p>The king being at Mantoue told a Gentleman of Lorete, that when he was at our Ladies there, he named himſelfe, <hi>Iuan Poeta.</hi> This Gentleman being entred into very good termes of amitie with the King, did him many kind fauours and courteſies, enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining him at his lodging in the beſt ſort he could deuiſe: and ſhortly after accompanied him to Ferrara, where he apparelled the King in ſilkes and veluet. Shortly after this Gentleman had performed theſe offices to the King, his vrgent buſineſſe called him from that place: but before he went, he conducted the King to his tailers houſe, and there tooke order for the ſupplying of his wants, and gaue great charge for his ſpeciall entertainment, willing his hoſt to call him <hi>Ioanne Baptiſta Sartori della contrada de Santa Maria la Fratra.</hi> This man was of good yeares, very ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and rich, into whoſe houſe the King entred the fourth of October, anno 1597. In which yeare, the King vnderſtanding the Pope was to make his entrie into Ferrara; accompanied with this tayler, about the firſt of May ſet forward towards the ſame citie: whither when the King came and found not his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines there, he determined then to attend his comming. In which ſpace the King confeſſed himſelfe to Frier <hi>Alonſo,</hi> a religious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor of my order, a man of great vertue and ſinceritie (but very ſimple) who thinking to do well, did that which fell out to be very ill, in reporting to diuers Nobles and Gentlemen, that <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the King of Portugale was in the citie, attending the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1393:29"/>preſence of his Holineſſe: and as it hapneth, that one euil ſeldom comes alone, the tayler being acquainted with a gentleman of Portugale (whoſe name I know not, ſome called him <hi>Baron</hi>) this Gentleman the tayler conducted home to the Kings lodging to diner. This Portugale ſitting at the table, often beheld the King aduiſedly as he ſate at meate, and obſerued him in euery reſpect. Soone after dinner was done, the King roſe and departed to his chamber. After his retire the Gentleman ſaid to his hoſteſſe, and the reſt of the company that dined with them, the tailor alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing preſent: <hi>Gentlemen</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>this Gentleman that ſate here at diner amongst vs, is ſurely</hi> D. Sebaſtian <hi>the King of Portugal. I am that countriman and know him well, for I haue ſeene him many times before his departure into Africke to warre againſt the Infidels. All we Portugals hold it for an aſſured veritie, that he eſcaped at that time very ſore hurt, and that he was ſeene afterward in Portugale, from whence he fled, but how or what way we could neuer yet learne.</hi> The tailor no ſooner heard theſe words, but he went preſently and told them to the king. This ſpeech much offended the king, and grieued him not a litle; and withall, remembring that Frier <hi>Alonſo</hi> had in his meere ſimplicitie betrayed him: and moreouer, conſidering that the King of Caſtiles Agent was aduertiſed that he was in that citie, and plotted againſt him, being in great feare what euill might happen vnto him, reſolued preſently to ſteale away ſecretly, without taking leaue either of hoſt, confeſſor, or taylor.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe the tailor himſelfe vttered vnto me, with many other particularities, in the temple of <hi>S. Silueſter</hi> in Verona, confirming the ſame in his owne houſe afterward, with the effuſion of abundant teares running downe his cheekes and beard, with ſuch zealous lamentation, as he inforced me to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie him in the ſelfe ſame manner of grieuing. He told me alſo that he remained in his houſe with him ſeuen moneths at the leaſt, and was atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on by his daughter, being a faire yong maiden: and in all that while he proteſted the King did not once looke directly in her face, commending him for his temperate, affable, and exceeding vertuous behauiour, and that he obſerued his faſts very ſeuerely, praying almoſt continually: and ſaid far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1393:29"/>vnto me weeping: <hi>Father, I feare that Prince is much iniured: I beſeech the Almightie God to preſerue him: O that it were lawfull for me, and for his ſafetie, that I might keepe him within my ſimple habitation, not as he is a Prince, but in reſpect of his bountie and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: and if I ſhould happen to die before him, I could leaue him ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to liue on all the dayes of his life.</hi> Truſt me the ſimplicitie of this poore old man, pleaſed me exceedingly, and induced me the rather to beleeue him. He alſo informed me by what title the Senate of Venice called him, and inquired of him if euer he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained him in his houſe, and whether his anſwers to diuers interrogatories were true or not, and whether all that he told the Lords were true or falſe? To which he anſwered iuſtly and failed not a iot; and he maintained him to be the true King of Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale, hauing many reaſons ſo to perſwade him: the one was the confident aſſertion of the Portugal gentleman that dined in his company at Ferrara, ſaying he departed out of Portugal ſecretly, yet proued by many circumſtances: and this old man aſſiſted me much when the Senate conuented him before them, asking him how long he kept companie with him before he came to Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, and whether he were the ſame man that lodged in his houſe. Then he kneeled downe before his feete, embracing them, and looking towards the Senate, ſaid: <hi>This is</hi> Dom Sebaſtian <hi>King of Portugale, which lodged in my houſe: whom afterward I accompanied to Ferrara.</hi> And when the king was asked of the Iudges, whether he knew that old man or no: he anſwered, that he had neuer ſeen him before this day. At which anſwer, the old man told me he was more perplexed, then he was with his ſudden departure from him at Ferrara, and wept moſt bitterly. I muſt excuſe the king for thus confuting the old man before the Senate, for that he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood at Venice and Padua, a litle after he departed from the preſence of the Senate, that they had ſtraightly impriſoned and puniſhed one <hi>Monſieur Ieronimo</hi> at Venice, for entertaining him into his houſe, and had puniſhed diuers other for doing him the like fauour. And the King fearing that the like rigour might be offered this ſilly old man, made him to diſclaime his acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: which the King vpon his returne to priſon, reuealed inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently to Count <hi>Caeſar Martinengo,</hi> to Count <hi>Charles</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1393:30"/>and diuers other his fellow priſoners. <hi>And the Lords ſaid vnto me, they called me to ſee one</hi> Iohn Baptiſta Sartori de Verona, <hi>and asked me if I knew him; and for that I was much bound to this good old man, for many good offices done vnto me, and for that I ſaw it turned them al to diſpleaſure, that did me any good, I anſwered for his ſafetie, that I knew him not, nor had euer ſeene him: which the poore old man digeſts very heauily: and if any good friend would but deliuer this my excuſe vnto him, I wil acknowlege my ſelf much bound to him for that friendly courteſie.</hi> The ſelfe ſame act in the like words, a Cannon of Breſſe reported vnto me, meeting me in that city, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panying me as far as Lac, hapning to ſpeake of the king, and of the opinion that was deliuered of them generally that had ſeene him: that it was thought verily he was <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> the king moſt aſſuredly, not knowing me to be any fauorer of his proceedings: telling me that al he knew of the matter, he heard of theſe Counts and gentlemen that were in priſon with him, for the ſpace of fiue moneths: whereof he recited vnto me many particulars: and this Cannon (as I take it) was called <hi>De Lone:</hi> ſo after long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference the night approching, I tooke my leaue of him, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The King departing from Ferrara, held on his way to Padua, and being there, he thought it fit he ſhould attend the anſwer of his letters he ſent into Portugale by <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone:</hi> his deuotion performed to <hi>S. Anthony,</hi> he determined to go to Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, where all theſe things happened vnto him, which we haue alreadie reported in the former treatiſe, intituled, <hi>Admirable Aduentures, &amp;c.</hi> as you may reade in a letter ſent to me from <hi>Iohn de Caſtro;</hi> &amp; in that, which the king wrote to his Holineſſe: where it is at large ſpecified, how he was betraied into the hands of the Caſtilians, by one of his owne ſeruants for reward, and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to priſon. This trecherous varlet being conuinced and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by ſome of the Kings friends, that had vnderſtanding of his perfidious ſeruice, being already bought and corrupted with a few pence, following the periured faction like a maiſterleſſe curre, fell into the art of ſlandering, and banding againſt his loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all maiſter with hote purſute, and vehement accuſations, as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domie, coſinage, in priſon and abroade. Notwithſtanding all this villanie, God that weyes all mens cauſes in equall ballance, will
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1393:30"/>not ſuffer his ſeruants euer to quaile vnder the burden of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: the hearing of his cauſe was committed to <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Marco Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini,</hi> which was at that time <hi>Sabio de la terre firme,</hi> and at this day is, <hi>Sabio Grande,</hi> one of the foure Iudges, commiſſioners allotted for this circuite. The ſaid <hi>Quirini</hi> reporting to the Senate what he had heard concerning his accuſations, and what alſo was te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified in his defence, ſaid, <hi>That he not only found this man innocent and guiltleſſe of the crimes laid to his charge, but thought him gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to haue liued a harmeleſſe life.</hi> This ſentence was well appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and allowed by the Senators: &amp; aſſoone as it was publiſhed, which was in the beginning of the yere 1599 they freed the king from the dungion where he lay before, and placed him in a more fauourable priſon, a place of ſome libertie. You ſhall reade here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after the paines and puniſhment <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the King my maiſter indured ſithence his miſaduenture in Africke, vntill the day of his manifeſtation to the world. I beſeech you hold me ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, though I ſatisfie you not ſo plentifully and ſo orderly as you expect or deſire: it is all I could learne, and it is hard to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo much in theſe parts, where the truth hath bene ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niouſly laboured to be ſuppreſſed and ſmoothered: beſide, the great hazard of my perſon in trauelling to obtaine this litle, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you that our hope withers not, but ſprings dayly, to ſee my Lord <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> to be as abſolute King of Portugale, as it is iuſtly due vnto him by the law of God and nations: then ſhall my pen trample vpon the vale of tyrannie and oppreſſion, that now ſo imperiouſly curbes poore patience and equitie.</p>
               <p>Seeing God hath hitherto bene both his lampe and ſhield, to lighten and guard him, through ſo many darke and dangerous ambuſhments: why ſhould we not be aſſured that he that can hath a purpoſe to make vs reioyce and wonder as much at his aduancement and dignitie, as his poore friends and ſeruants are grieued and diſmayed with his fall and miſerie: hoping all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, magnificent, and maieſticall Princes will ioyne in inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to the Almightie, to reſtore my poore (yet princely Maiſter) from his wofull impiſonment, to his Crowne and libertie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:1393:31"/>
               <head>A Declaration.</head>
               <p>NOw it is requiſite, that I report vnto you ſomewhat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ring, that hath bene ſo famous throughout the world, and of the rare vertues it was eſteemed for: and ſo forward to handle other matters, whereof ſome make for his purpoſe, and other ſome as much for his hinderance.</p>
               <p>You haue heard (gentle Reader) of one that ſhewed this King a ring, &amp;c. thus it happened. As ſoone as he was come to Venice, there was warning giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the goldſmiths, both by him ſelfe and ſome other of his friends, that he was robbed of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine peeces of gold and iewels at Rome: then he gaue them the markes and tokens; deſiring them, that if any ſuch came into their hands by chaunce, they would make ſtay of them, vntill he, or ſome for him, came to chalenge them. Not long after, a goldſmith lighted vpon a ring of gold, wherein was grauen the Armes of Portugale: which ring he preſently brought to <hi>Monſieur Ieronimo,</hi> of whom you haue read before, an inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant of the ſame towne, who was ioyntly apprehended with the King for lodging in his houſe, and was not deliuered vntill fiue houres after the King was ſet at libertie. <hi>Ieronimo</hi> tooke the ring and brought it ſecretly to the King, lodging priuily in his houſe. Aſſoone as the King beheld the ring, he ſaid; This ring is none of mine, but it belongs to <hi>D. Anthony</hi> my coſin. This rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I had from <hi>Ieronimo</hi> himſelfe at Venice, in the preſence of many witneſſes, and how the goldſmith happened to get this ring. In Moran an Iland ſome halfe league from Venice, there is an Abbot called <hi>Capelo,</hi> a gentleman of Venice, a graue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage, and of great authoritie, hearing that the King laid waite for certaine iewels that he had loſt, hoping thereby to recouer ſome of them; hauing a diamond in his keeping, with the armes of Portugale, came to the towne to the conuenticles of <hi>S. Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis,</hi> called Frari, where the King lay concealed, for that he was purſued by ſome that meant him no good; who no ſooner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the ring, but he ſaid: Verily this is mine; and I either loſt the ſame in Flanders, or elſe it was ſtolne from me. And when the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1393:31"/>King had put it vpon his finger, it appeared otherwiſe ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen then before. The Abbot inquiring of him that brought him the ring, how he came by it: he anſwered, It is true that the King hath ſaid. Therehence aroſe a ſtrange rumour of a ring, that by turning the ſtone you might diſcerne three great letters engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: <hi>S. R. P.</hi> that is as much to ſay: <hi>Sebaſtianus Rex Portugalliae.</hi> Ignorant people not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiuing aright of the thing, raiſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſuch rumours, as their owne imaginations could gather: and at all times, ſo often as the Abbot ſhewed the ring to the King, he had many witneſſes to teſtifie the ſame. I ſoiourned three weekes in the ſame Ile, very neare the Abbots houſe, after this had paſt.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond point: although the King were leane and weake by reaſon of his trauell and troubles, as it is like he could not be ſo ſtrong and puiſſant as he was when he raigned in Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugale, being there full fed and corpulent: yet in Padua in the houſe of <hi>D. Proſpero Baracco,</hi> he was ſeene to lift vp two men at once with great facilitie, one of the which was called <hi>Paſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Moroſini,</hi> the other <hi>Bernardino Santi;</hi> both theſe together (put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his arme betweene their legs) he heaued from the ground, without ſtraining or wrenching in the view of many. He did the like in the Ile of Moran to two other, the one called <hi>Ieronimo Calegari,</hi> the other <hi>Paſcalino Calegari;</hi> and there was preſent the Archbiſhop of Spalato at the like performance of his puiſſance with other men of qualitie: and this <hi>Paſquilino</hi> was a man both tall and corpulent. A Venetian gentleman of the houſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the the King was priſoner, oftentimes took occaſion to ſcoffe at the king, ſaying: It was impoſſible he ſhould be the perſon he reported himſelf to be, with other geering frumpes: whereto the King ſaid earneſtly: Sir, I pray you tell me the reaſon of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulitie, and whereupon it is grounded: and <hi>Moliner</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: Becauſe I haue heard it often reported, that the King <hi>Dom Sebastian</hi> was a luſty ſtrong man, of power to pul a horſe-ſhooe in ſunder with his hands, and able to tire ſixe horſes in an houre; and you are but a ſpare poore megar ſhrimpe, and a griſtle in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ſuch a one, and ſcarcely able to teare foure cards aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if they be well ioyned together, nor like to tire one horſe in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1393:32"/>an houre. Well, ſaid the King, if force will prooue me to be <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> &amp;c. and the matter reſt onely vpon that, it may be that one day I may ſatisfie you in that point. So long this galla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in his former geering and railing, that one day aboue the reſt, he moued the Kings patience, and made him angrie, and conſtrained him to ſhew him by the force of his hands, that he was <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> &amp;c. and made him confeſſe the ſame: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a rage he came vpon him directly, and tooke him by the girdle with his right hand, and heauing him higher the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his head, caried him round about the priſon in that manner, to the great admiration of all that beheld it: and this Gentleman neuer after durſt abuſe him any more, but vſed him with the honour and reuerence that was due vnto him. In like manner, he tooke vp in the ſame priſon by the girdle one <hi>Gasparo Turloni</hi> (a Gentleman of Venice) with his right hand, and <hi>Baptiſte Marſoto</hi> with his left hand, and lifted them both vp from the ground at one time. He alſo in the ſame priſon tooke vp (putting his arme betweene their legges) two other Gentlemen, one very groſſe and corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent (namely <hi>Meſſier Lucio de Meſſine,</hi> and <hi>Alexander de Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi>) and lifted them both of a good height: the oportunitie of this Gentleman made him do it in priſon: and at Padua, and at Moran he was diſpoſed to ſhew his force, to pleaſure his friends thereby. That which before was ſpoken of the ring, and of his forces, were the two things I thought neceſſarie firſt to giue you notice of.</p>
               <p>To ad to the two firſt two other. In Venice there is a rich and an honourable merchant; who hearing of this King, what marks and tokens he had on his bodie, and what he had ſaid and done, tooke occaſion to go to him, and made meanes to deſerue his loue and amitie, by the performance of many kind offices to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him. This merchant was a Piemontoiſe by nation, by name called <hi>Monſieur Iohn Baſſaneſſe,</hi> and his mother being a widow maried after to one <hi>Bartholomaeo Verneti,</hi> a Piemontoiſe borne alſo: who often vſed to checke and reprooue his ſonne in law for going ſo much to the King, ſaying, he was am impoſtor and a counterfeit: and his ſon in law boldly defended the King, by all the meanes and reaſons he could deuiſe. During this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1393:32"/>betwixt the father and the ſon in law, the old man ſaid; Come hither, heare me: <hi>Emanuel Philibert</hi> Duke of Sauoy, ſent an Ambaſſador to <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> king of Portugal his nephew, ſonne to his coſin germaine, which Ambaſſador brought him a preſent; and returned backe againe from the ſaid King with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: and another preſent from the King to the Duke, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors name was <hi>Dominico Belli,</hi> whoſe ſeruant I was at that very inſtant, by meanes whereof I ſaw and was priuie to all the parcels, and placed them my ſelfe in the casket, and likewiſe ſaw aduiſedly what was returned from the King. Now ſit, if you can perſwade that man that ſays he is <hi>D. Sebaſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp;c. to tel me what parcels thoſe were (that were ſent to and fro) directly, you ſhall bring me to be of your mind, and to confeſſe that he is the very ſame man he nominates himſelfe to be. <hi>Iohn Baſſaneſſe</hi> hearing theſe words, bethought himſelfe which way he might come to haue conference with the King, to vnderſtand the right of this matter, &amp; as he was ſtudying how to bring his purpoſe about, he dreamed of a ſtratageme which ſhould effect his deſigne, which was, that he wold perpetrate ſome light crime, in hope therfore to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to the priſon, where the king was: wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued to take a cudgel vnder his cloake &amp; go to the Realto, the chiefeſt place in Venice, and there quarel with one or other, and baſtinado him vntil he had drawn bloud of him, for which act he doubted not but to be committed: he proceeded according to his ſecret determination, and when he was come neare the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alto, he met with a friend of his, who perceiuing by his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanee, that he was troubled in mind, ſaid vnto him: Sir, I ſee by you there is ſomewhat amiſſe. <hi>Iohn Baſſaneſſe</hi> being wel aſſured, that he was a faithfull ſeruant to the King, laid open his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vnto him, who found a meanes to get a note in writing vnder the kings hand of all the parcels, that paſſed from the one to the other. This memorandum was put into the hands of one <hi>Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nardo Donato,</hi> one of the <hi>Sabio grande,</hi> that firſt examined the King, and was thought to owe him litle good will, but after he ſurueyed his cauſe, and found it ſo iuſt &amp; true, trauelled earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Senate, to pronounce him <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the true king of Portugal. All this I haue heard confirmed by many very wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1393:33"/>perſons: the originall I could not bring with me, for that <hi>Donato</hi> at my being there was employed as Generall of fiue and twentie thouſand foote, and fiue thouſand horſe, in the countie of Broſſe: which force the Siegniorie had leauied the yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for their defence vpon ſome intelligence, &amp;c. But as ſoone as <hi>Iohn Baſſaneſſe</hi> had got the writing, he hyed him home to his father in law, and they agreed betweene them, that one ſhould ſtand at one end of the table, and the other below; and the father wrote the peeces he knew, and the ſon by his note was able to informe the old man of diuers parcels that he had forgotten: and the old man ſaid it was haſt made him ouerſlip ſomewhat; thoſe foure white horſes (ſaid he) I did not well remember, but I thinke verily it was true: and the old man wondred not a little, how his ſonne came by this intelligence, and ſaid he had deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it himſelfe: but ſeeing himſelfe vanquiſhed, ſaid to his ſonne: Viſit the King, my ſon, at your pleaſure, and do him what good you may, and I beſeech God to aſſiſt him.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as I know the curious ſort of people, deſire to view the particulars, and to make our proofe the more autenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, I haue here ſet the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> down in order as they were inuentoried.</p>
               <q>The parcels preſented by the Duke to the King.</q>
               <p>A caſe full of ſilkes, of diuers colours.</p>
               <p>Another full of cloth of ſiluer, of diuers ſorts and colours.</p>
               <p>Another full of cloth of gold, of diuers colours.</p>
               <p>A diamond ſet in a ring.</p>
               <p>An auncient garment of very great value, being a trophe, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the French at <hi>S. Quintaines,</hi> embrodered &amp; garniſhed about the necke with many iewels, foure white horſes which the old man had forgotten, and diuers other peeces not named.</p>
               <q>Thoſe parcels that were ſent from the King to the Duke.</q>
               <p>A great chaine of gold of very good value: two peutrils, two bits, two paire of ſtirops, all garniſhed with diamonds, rubies, and other ſtones of great price.</p>
               <p>One diamond ſet in gold, which <hi>Bartholomeo Veneti</hi> ſaid was as big as the naile of his right thombe.</p>
               <p>Many Eaſt-Indian diſhes of ſundrie colours, with other rich things of good eſteeme.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:1393:33"/>
               <p> For the ſecond of the laſt proofes, being the fourth and laſt, you ſhall vnderſtand that there be foure merchants at Venice, men indued with wealth, honour, eſtimation, and charitie, that in my hearing haue named theſe foure witneſſes <hi>Barnaba Rizzo, Iean Baſſaneſſe, Conſtantin Nicoli,</hi> who keeps in his hand the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal letter of <hi>D. Raimond Marqueti,</hi> by which it is manifeſt that <hi>D. Sebaſtian</hi> is one man, and <hi>Marco Tullio Catizzone</hi> another: which letter he ſhewed publickely at <hi>S. Markes,</hi> to conuince the falſhood of the Caſtilians, and their adherents: for the which and ſuch other like ſeruices, the Spaniards could not be appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without reuenge. The nineteenth of October, I had intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence by letters, that one came into this honeſt mans ſhop, his ſeruants being ſent all out of the way, and cut him on the head with a curtelaxe, and in diuers other places ſo dangerouſly, that he was in great perill of his life. The malefactor eſcaped vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne. The fourth and laſt is called <hi>Baptiſte Dolphine,</hi> and theſe foure haue bene euer good friends to the King, both by entertaining him and trauelling in his affaires, to the vttermoſt of their power, to ſet him at libertie, without intermiſſion of any minute of oportunitie, that might be ſpent in his profitable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. But the Caſtilian Agents conſidering and knowing the zeale of theſe perſonages, and obſeruing their conſtancie, that both with all their might and maine, defended the cauſe of the King my maiſter: ſeeing that neither faire promiſes, perſwaſions, nor threatnings, could make them deſiſt from their vowed fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and aſſiſtance, entred into this diuelliſh practiſe. Firſt they beganne to publiſh theſe witneſſes to be fooles, coſiners, and rogues, and perſwaded certaine bankers and brokers to lay wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers with them, that the priſoner was not <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the King: aſſuring them that they might offer to giue a thouſand for one, if euer it were prooued or publiſhed; for that they knew aſſuredly, that he was a Calabrian, a Sodomite, a theefe, a coſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and a counterfeit, and that ere long they ſhould ſee him hanged vpon one of the pillars of <hi>S. Markes</hi> Church. Theſe vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers beleeuing this to be true, and deſirous to make gaine of any thing, beganne to enter into the courſe of laying wagers, as the Caſtilians had aduiſed them. The witneſſes hearing they
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1393:34"/>offered ſo franckly a thouſand for one, if the priſoner were iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be <hi>Dom Sebaſtian,</hi> &amp;c. knowing certainly that it was he: beleeuing that the Senate, in regard of ſuch eſpeciall markes; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and proofes, would not refuſe to publiſh him, what they had found him: were eaſily drawne to bargaine with theſe ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, to ſome of the which, the ſimple and honeſt men gaue out twentie, ſome thirtie, ſome fiftie, ſome ten, ſome fiue crownes, in hope to be paid a thouſand for one: ſo that they had giuen out ſome three hundred crownes or more; and ſhortly after they found out the wrong and hindrance they had done to the poore Kings cauſe, by their mony, they begun to repent themſelues ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly of their folly: the account was caſt, that the repaiment would amount to three hundred thouſand crownes. And the bankers ſeeing themſelues ingaged for ſo great a ſum of monie; and if the Senate ſhould chance to publiſh that which they knew to be true, that they were like to be ſtripped of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of their ſubſtance, began to complot and oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to counterchecke the truth, which fell out to be a great preiudice and barre to the King my maiſters cauſe; for that many chiefe men, and the factors of many principall hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were intereſted in this hazard of indemnitie: as thoſe of the houſe of <hi>Aſtroci, Caponi, Baglioni, Labia, Iacobo Begia, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio Simone, Pietro Tobon, Baſtian Garinoni,</hi> and many others of their parents and allies, for their ſakes: among which were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers that bare office in the common-weale, as <hi>Iacobo Fuſcurini</hi> a proctor in <hi>S. Marke,</hi> that was euer enemie to the King my maiſter. In the end this diuelliſh inuention, and Caſtilian perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pollicie, wrought vs much woe, and multiplied our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies infinitely: for it was ſo commonly knowne and ſpoken, that litle children as they went for muſtard, could ſay, that this was the principall cauſe why the Senators would haue had <hi>Dom Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian</hi> ſay, he was not <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> but a Calabrian, and they promiſed ſtraight to ſet him at libertie; and not that fauour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but they would do what elſe for him, he could or would require. Whereupon he wrote a letter to the Pope, complaining iuſtly vpon the Senators of Venice, for requiring at his hands ſo vnlawfull a thing, to whom he declared in his letter, that he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1393:34"/>them, that he had rather die a tortured death, then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe ſo palpable an vntruth, to gaine an ignominious life and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie. O that it were poſſible for me to ſpeake all that is true in this caſe! but I muſt let paſſe infinite iniuries, leaſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealing all, might rather aggraute then relieue my maiſters mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie. If I durſt, this diſcourſe ſhould haue bene more ample, and better vnderſtood, if it were lawful that I might ſay what I could ſay, that the Monarks and Princes of Chriſtendome, haue done the King my Lord ſecretly and openly much good and ill, and are vnwilling either of both ſhould be manifeſted to the world in writing. Notwithſtanding I will neuer burie in ſilence an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer that a grand Sabio of this commonwealth made to a mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Prince in Europe, of great vnderſtanding, but of no great antiquitie. This <hi>Sabio</hi> going to viſite this Prince, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by him to tell him what ground the Seigniorie of Venice had, to proceed vpon the priſoner in that forme, which called himſelfe <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portugale? for (ſaid he) if they found him to be a Calabrian, why did they ſet him at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie without chaſtiſement? And if it were verified vnto them by good proofes and euidence that he was <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> King of Portugal, why did they vſe him in that maner? The grand <hi>Sabio</hi> publikely made this anſwer in the preſence of many. Sir, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as the affaires concerned the eſtate of Spaine, the Seignio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie would not preſume to iudge whether it was he or not. This man was committed for diſobeying a commaundement the Seigniorie laid vpon him, and therefore reſtrained two yeares of his libertie, to the end he might repent him of his fault, and after the expiration of two yeares againe diſmiſſed him vpon the like commaundement. And to be plaine with your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie: the man would follow no good aduice, but was wilfull, turbulent, and of ill gouernement, by which meanes much ill is come vnto him. That word ill aduiſed, might haue bene well interpreted, for that he would not denie himſelfe to be that which vndoubtedly he was. It was not my fortune to be preſent at this act, being elſewhere employed out of thoſe parts: but at my returne it was related to me, by a learned perſon that was there in preſent; which afterward the ſame Prince himſelfe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1393:35"/>did ratifie vnto me, aſſuring me that the anſwer of that <hi>Sabio</hi> grand, did verily induce him to beleeue, that that priſoner was <hi>Dom Sebaſtian</hi> the very true King of Portugale: for if the Seigniorie had held this man to be a Calabrian: ſaid this Prince, to what purpoſe did the <hi>Sabio</hi> hold me with ſuch a long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe publickely, conſidering he knew the priuitie of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires; if he had bene proued a Calabrian, it had bene ſufficient to haue ſaid in a word; Sir, he was a Calabrian, an impoſtor, and a coſiner, without any more ado. But you ſee how the world fares, and how it ſwayes abruptly, and ſo ends my pitifull nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; aduiſing, intreating, and coniuring you (gentle Reader) to ſhun the ſnares and trips of theſe ſubtill enemies: for I can aſſure you, by the teſtimonie of a good conſcience, that they be thoſe that <hi>S. Chryſoſtome</hi> terme the Phariſes, <hi>Qui portabant mel in ore, &amp; fel in corde:</hi> they will flap you in the mouth with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, which when you begin to chew, perhaps you ſhall taſte ſweete, but in the digeſtion, you ſhall find it moſt bitter in operation. Farewell.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:1393:35"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
